<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Doctor Hill's funeral-sermon. Or a nevv-yeers-gift to all the clergie. Daynus, the reviving feet fo the witnesses past and to come, to shew the day and yeer of the Lord, and his time accepted.</title>
            <author>Hesselwood, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E821_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866699</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866699</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118983</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86096)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118983)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E821[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Doctor Hill's funeral-sermon. Or a nevv-yeers-gift to all the clergie. Daynus, the reviving feet fo the witnesses past and to come, to shew the day and yeer of the Lord, and his time accepted.</title>
                  <author>Hesselwood, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>And are to be sold by Richard Moon at the the seven stars in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, 1654. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts.</note>
                  <note>The second part starts with a new register on p.1, has caption-title: The second part of D. Hils funeral-sermon, with his apollation to priests and people. By me Henry Hasselwood and running title: The second part of Dr. Hill's funeral-sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Doctor <hi>HILL</hi>'s FUNERAL-SERMON. OR, A Nevv-yeers-Gift To all the CLERGIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daynus,</hi> the reviving feet of the Witneſſes paſt and to come, To ſhew the day and yeer of the Lord, and his time accepted.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1654. And are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Moon</hi> at the ſeven Stars in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:2"/>
            <head>His Epiſtle and Dedication to the Clergy.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou ſoweſt all life in the fleſh, and thou reapeſt life to thy ſelf, O Lord: thou windeſt up life in the body of life; thou art the Center and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of quickning life: All Creatures move in the power of that life. That ſubſtance of fleſh by procreation is not that ſaving life, but thou art the quinteſſence of all life in the Soul. The Soul in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural condition is <hi>vayla,</hi> and changeable by the inſtinct of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture included in the fleſh; <hi>varra,</hi> changeable in it ſelf; <hi>fayla,</hi> not able to ſtand, unleſs it be redeemed by an incluſive power ſpiritual: and in that way God will be ſeen to deliver, by way of imputation of life to the Soul: <hi>Reeda Alda,</hi> at every ſeaſon <hi>Helpative Soona, Plyant Dative,</hi> by a dividual dividing betwixt the Marrow and the Bones; Circumference, <hi>Deus All-fulneſs, Unus varius, Allmagnus,</hi> God the full beauty and life, in him all things are computed, comprized, and comprehended by him; he is <hi>All meritus</hi> and <hi>tranſlatirus,</hi> and doth refine all things: he is the final and fountain of all perfection, the life and death of all the Creatures: every thing that moveth liveth in him. All ſoleſtial fleſh is as a flower or graſs that withereth away, and ſhall be no more in its natural perfection: for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall live but life, that ſhall not dy, which is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God in thee, called that immortality, which is a ſpiritual reviving power that ſhall return to God; although the fleſh doth not, yet the ſpirit ſhall return to him that gave it. The Soul is the life of the Creation naturally in us, prohibited and preſented by him, which is our life ſo preſerved. The Spirit
<pb facs="tcp:118983:3"/> is an incluſive thing of union, and by an immortal marriage it hath congruity with the Soul: the Soul is a high myſtery, it is the Virgin of the ſpirit, and the ſpirit dwelleth in it, till the fleſh dieth, which maketh a diſſolution betwixt fleſh and ſoul. The ſpirit of grace is an high myſtery, and dwelleth in ſome, but not in all: every one may have life in them, yet not that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual life, which is the life of eternity: therefore none can live after the old <hi>Adam,</hi> but ſhall dy the death, until the quickning power of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> come in, which is Chriſt in thee and in me, to renew in us that which would die: for nothing carnally can live. The ſoul is naturally ſowed in the fleſh, and is of it ſelf fleſhly by four natural cauſes, by a Soveraingty from God; as Breath, blood, Heat and Food, which keepeth thy natural ſoul alive: there is a threefold life; two of them be but natural life, as vegetive life, natural life, and ſpiritual life, and all have their being from that eternal life: We ſee many times that young fleſh droppeth off from the Tree of life; the aged muſt do ſo, the King muſt die as well as the Beggar, ſo muſt the high Doctor as well as the ſilly poor man; then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with me the period of mans life, and full of brevity, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding changeable ſmoak, or as a vapor that ſoon paſſeth away. So much for mans mortality. The next thing is to enquire and ſpeak ſomething of this our late deceaſed Brother Doctor <hi>Hill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:3"/>
            <head>Doctor HILL'S Funeral-Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y a ſingular providence of God I happened to be at the Town of</hi> Cambridge <hi>at the very inſtant of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> Hill's <hi>departure: then at the ſame time the Lord moved me to write, and he actually taught me what I ſhould write, which he the Lord preached to me. This Sermon preached to me was not my deſire onely, yet the God of life put it upon me, and ſupported me with matter accordingly, that I could not deny but write: for the Lord preached unto me the things I ſhould write, and now I declare unto you a new Sabbath, which I did write with much niceneſs and fear of ſpirit; yet the Lord told me that the Sabbath-Ordinances were changed by the Prieſts under the Law, and likewiſe by the Miniſters of our time. And therefore of neceſſity I did write as he commanded me, by way of a Funeral-Sermon, or a final diſſolution of the Clergellical power, whereof I declare the life and death of the Creature, and the ſtability and endleſs power of Chriſts Miniſtery, with a deſcription of them that call themſelves Miniſters of God, and how they ſhall fall under the Worlds contempt, ſome degrees worſe then the Biſhops. The Prophets complaine; the clamation is, The Miniſter and Prieſts have robbed Gods ſtore-houſe, taking to themſelves thoſe priviledges that are not their own; therefore they ſhall ſay no more, Know the Lord from the greateſt to the leaſt; and ſhall be free from your
<pb facs="tcp:118983:4"/> mouth inherently taught of God, and live by faith exemplary to</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Noah, <hi>and Chriſt; which is to live in righteouſneſs, and not to need the teachings of men: for all our teachers are failable now as well as they were under the Law; ſo that our redemption is clearly by Chriſt,</hi> Heb. 7.24. <hi>Chriſt he continued ever unchangeable as a Prieſt, whereof he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come to God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them: which is a plaine proof, without diſpute, that he is the Miniſter of God, and Prieſt; he will put an end to your Miniſtery, becauſe you are failable, yet Chriſt is infailable: and therefore we caſt you off in the name of the Lord, and cry ye down as no Miniſters of God, but deceivers of the people. I would bave all live up to Chriſt by a perſonal power, free from all the teachings of men, and that no man ſhall ought to teach, whether he be a Miniſter or a lay-man; for one mans tongue is no lawful teſtimony, for one may ſpeak of Chriſt as well as another, ſo that</hi> all may propheſy one by one, <hi>as they did in Chriſts time: for</hi> in the laſt dayes I will pour out my ſpirit upon all fleſh, for my ſervants and handmaids ſhall propheſie. Then ſaid he unto me, Propheſie, ſon of man: So I propheſied as he commanded me, and the breath came into them, and they lived and ſtood upon their feet, an exceeding great Army. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37. <hi>This Army Giddon of the Lord ſhall cauſe the River</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates <hi>with ſeven ſtreams to dry up; and there ſhall be many voyces heard, and witneſſes on their Feet. Then looke to it Doctor; without all diſpute, your trade of preaching will fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEloved, this Doctor <hi>Hill</hi> was a man of good ranke, an eminent man that I did formerly know, though now he was very juſtitious; I was his Country-man about ſixteen or eighteen yeers paſt; he was a reaſonable good profeſſor called a Puritan in thoſe dayes; but what he was now, I cannot tell; I hear you ſay he was Maſter of Trinity-Colledge. This Doctor <hi>Hill</hi> was very well known and approved of through all the Univerſity of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge;</hi> This Doctor <hi>Hill</hi> was a man very well beloved in the Town, it rung paſſing-peals for him at five Churches, which I have ſeldome heard ſo many Bells of <hi>Aaron</hi> ring for one Prieſt. You tell me he had neither Son nor Daughter; what did he do with all his hundreds a yeer? did he build Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals for the poor? Ye tell me he was a man of little Hoſpitality; then I cannot ſpeak much in his behoof.</p>
            <p>The words that I ſhall treat upon are from the mouth of thoſe four Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37. <hi>Matthew</hi> 28. <hi>Zachariah</hi> 11. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. Theſe four Scriptures are the very ground-work of what we ſhall treat upon. We, even we the witneſſes, foreſhow the myſtery of thoſe Evangelical Prophets, and one Angelical amongſt the reſt, Chriſt the firſt, <hi>Ezekiel, Zachary,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118983:4"/> and <hi>John,</hi> by inference doth plainly type out the two Teſtaments of Law and Goſpel, declaring of two Scriptures, one before Chriſt came in the fleſh, the other by a Teſtimony of Chriſt and <hi>John,</hi> ſaying: <hi>I come not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfil the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we may finde theſe Prophets were part of the Witneſſes that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after Chriſt: ſo that theſe four Scriptures make out one teſtimony, which one Scripture cannot do ſo affirmatively, for one Scripture muſt prove another, and ſo make out truth which is undeniable.</p>
            <p>Theſe four Prophets, though far diſtant in their times, yet declared out the great things of God to come in our dayes, the one by a <hi>fooliſh Shephard</hi> that God will raiſe, ſpoken of by <hi>Zachary</hi> long before; the other are the two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that God will raiſe and put life into, and ſhall ſtand upon their Feet: it is not one mans feet, but feet of Witneſſes; it is one Prieſt one Prophet alone which is Chriſt Jeſus ſingular of himſelf, &amp; not for man to ſtand as Doctor De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finator; and as one man cannot prove a truth, ſo two Scriptures muſt of neceſſity make out one truth which is a vindicated truth, and tolerated of God by Law and teſtimony.</p>
            <p>But you high Doctors may queſtion me in this thing, why one Scripture can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be tolerable as well as two.</p>
            <p>My anſwer is, becauſe the Mount <hi>Sion</hi> came between the Law and Goſpel, and changed the courſe of <hi>Sinai</hi> to Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> which is one to the Lord: for Chriſt ſtandeth in power of himſelf to prove every Scripture, which is an allegory, or an all-power of himſelf, which man cannot attain unto: he is the high-Prieſt that firſt entred into reſt: he hath trod the winepreſs alone; ſo that none can ſtand chiefe of himſelf, but he alone, after the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedeck</hi> a Prieſt for ever ordained and ſent of God: he is our Miniſter, and no other.</p>
            <p>Doctor, I pray throw down your power; you are but as other men jointly to plead among your Low equals, and not to ſtand Lord Prieſt above others, preaching in your cauſe, to ſilence others. <hi>Therefore take to thy ſelf the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of a fooliſh Shepherd:</hi> Shewing that God will deliver his mind to ſome poor deſpiſed Shepherd, that ſhall declare his hand of judgement upon the Shepherds, to tell them they are but as other men, and ſhall acknowledge themſelves as Sheep among others, and not think ſo high of themſelves as to be called by the name of Shepherds: for Chriſt is all our Shepherd, and we are his Sheep, both Miniſter and People; neither ſhall you have power to ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannize over the conſciences of the People, for all things ſhall be judged by the Church-Community to make out the Propheſie of the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> by way of alluſion reſpondent or reſponſive to Chriſt; or under Chriſt, that ſome fooliſh Shepherd ſhould declare and ſtand up as a Fool amongſt the learned, ſaying, <hi>Take to thy ſelf the inſtruments of a fooliſh Shepherd.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:5"/>
            <p>Now what be thoſe inſtruments?</p>
            <p>To anſwer, they be two, and of no leſs number: for one is not to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered, but accompted as one inſtrument; it is one witneſs, and that is Chriſts place from God, and it not is tolerable for one man to preach and declare of himſelf in his own tongue, to ſilence the people; if he doth, his teſtimony is not true: for <hi>I will give power to my two witneſſes, and they ſhall propheſie;</hi> meaning, that two or three may propheſie, preach, or diſciply, and anſwer each other in order: ſo that I finde one alone, whether he be a Miniſter or a lay-man, of himſelf, cannot be tolerable to ſpeak; for the plural number ſhall extinguiſh the ſingular, Chriſt excepted: for he ſaith, <hi>By the mouth of two or three witneſſes every truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed;</hi> Chriſt ſaith, his own teſtimony could not be true, except his Father bore witneſs with him. So that he always appeared to two or more; the two <hi>Maries</hi> ſought him early in the morning. It ſheweth to us, that theſe women were two faithful witneſſes, in that he ſaid, <hi>Go make known my reſurrection,</hi> which was a calling of them by way of ordination, which Calling all you Doctors and Senators cannot ſhew. Again, when he appeared to <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, the babe ſprung in her wombe for joy.</hi> Again, he appears to the two that were going to <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus,</hi> which cauſed them to ſay, <hi>Did not our hearts burn within us, when he talked with us?</hi> So that talking of God is the beſt preaching, and will cauſe all you Miniſters to come down from your high places, I mean your Pulpits, and to plead among your low equals: for it is not the partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of one mans tongue that can be found lawful; for Chriſt ever appeared to two, which were the leaſt number; ſomtimes to three; ſomtimes to the twelve, that they might make out the truth: for the witneſſes muſt prove a true teſtimony; two or three witneſſes may make a true diſcovery, but one cannot. He ſaith, <hi>I will give power to two;</hi> that is not to one Miniſter, he cannot fully diſciply truth: for every divine truth is proved by witneſſes. That which one affirmeth in a Pulpit, another may deny; it is verily ſo in our common Churches. The truth ſhould be reaſoned out by faithful wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Where two or three be gathered in my name, I will be in the midſt of them;</hi> which is a great promiſe, or a calling forth of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to ſtand up and plead againſt the approbation of one Miniſters tongue, which is unlawful, for one man to deffinate or define a truth of himſelf, to ſeſſerate or deceive the people, calling himſelf a Miniſter of God.</p>
            <p>Ye Diviners, Flatterers, and Soothſayers, that carry the power in your own tongues, and yet no faithful witneſſes, which of you will loſe all for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Chriſt, to vindicate thy life, to ſacrifice thy liberty or thy parſonage for the truth of Chriſt? Alas you carry on the truth of God by flattery, and ſo deceive the hearers; you ſtand deffinating and temporing, ſowing Pillows under great Mens Elbows: you will ſpeak a little of Covetouſneſs, but much
<pb facs="tcp:118983:5"/> leſs of blood and oppreſſion, and little or nothing of devouring one another; for that will touch my ſelf, or my parſonage.</p>
            <p>O draw the Curtain there, ſee that God is angry with you, and telleth you by his Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> 3. that <hi>ye ſhall move out of your holes;</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiel</hi> the Prophet ſaith, <hi>The people ſhall be taken from your mouth;</hi> and <hi>Zachary</hi> ſaith, <hi>I heard a howling of the Shepherds, for their glory was ſpoiled:</hi> and <hi>Malachy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ye rob my Store-houſe, therfore the land is curſed with a curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ye Miniſters ſhould preach againſt all Impropriations, as that ye dare not do, for loſing your Parſonages, loſe them and loſe all; for then preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will ceaſe, and there will be many that will remove our Feet from the Pulpit; when every truth ſhall be defined by two or three witneſſes, what will becom of us Pulpittians? it will be to us as the mourning of <hi>Hadadrim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi> indeed that is the way to bring down the pride of <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum</hi> exalted ſo high: you Pulpitſayons are ſet ſo high, as Lord ſpeaker, who ſhall controul you? yet your power muſt come down; when your Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits ſhall have never a leg, yet the two witneſſes ſhall be upon their Feet, to plead for equity and juſtice, which ye do not; ye preach for your own ends, and cannot ſatisfie truth; alwaies full of repetition, but nothing of any new work that God will do in the earth. If a lay-man ſhould ſpeak higher things then thoſe you declare, you would ſay as <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> that he was mad. Ye have ſlandered many good Chriſtians that have been faithful wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to Chriſt, and learned the language from the Heavenly Univerſity, far paſſing <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly we have many Doctors in <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> that enjoy ſo much, that it is intolerable: Theſe blind Doctors, Doctor up the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and deceive the people; impropriating to themſelves more then Food and Rayment, which is contrary to Chriſts example; they be more in ſhew then in ſubſtance, getting to themſelves high tolerations which are not of Chriſt; whereof you ſhall lie under his wrath, ſaying, <hi>How hard a thing is it for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet take to thy ſelf the inſtruments of a fooliſh Shepherd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctor, I am as a fool amongſt the Doctors; I cannot but tell you the truth: for God hath raiſed my ſpirit, he hath encouraged me to ſpeak of your ſhame, and not to be daunted. Some Miniſters now of late have made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Doctors, hoping for ſome of theſe great places in <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> which will prove but veynal, or a veyne uncurable, that runneth it ſelf out by many obſtructions or claſhings one againſt another, Miniſter againſt Miniſter: there is not that Antipathy nor that Univerſality, for ſome ſhall preach up their power, and ſome ſhall preach it down. This Eclipſe or terrible ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will hold until the power of your Prieſthood fall: at the power of the
<pb facs="tcp:118983:6"/> eternal Prieſt, you muſt throw down your power at Chriſts Feet; for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſhall be all our teacher. Miniſters, your mouthes ſhall be ſtopped, <hi>Micah</hi> 3. you ſhall not divine, <hi>you ſhall no more ſay to the people, Know the Lord for they ſhall all know me from the greateſt to the leaſt;</hi> and that is by ſpiritual revelation, or by an inward knowing, which far paſſeth your learned places; your Colledges are filled with many ſcandalous Ruffinous Fellows and of a ranting Crew, very litteral, and not knowing the truth; tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and uſurping the word of the letter to their own turnes, ſetting themſelves higher then the teachings of God, thinking lay-men inferior to themſelves; as if God could not raiſe up Children to <hi>Abraham</hi> out of thoſe Stones.</p>
            <p>To be taught of God, is the beſt Univerſity: for all your wit, and skill, and univeſality of tongues, cannot make one godly perſon: for <hi>every gift and perfect giving is from above.</hi> God miniſtreth grace to whom he pleaſeth; he is the Miniſter; then how canſt thou be a Miniſter? for God miniſtreth to all things; then yeild up thy Prieſthood to him; he is the Fountaine, and all the Streames muſt go to that Fountaine. You Doctors are ſet ſo high, and ſhall become low, more contemptible then the Biſhops were: for God will ſet you as a mark to ſhoot at, or as a loſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for the Bittern or Owle to ſit in; for you have kept all things at a diſtance, blinding the people, and keeping them under the letter by the hearing of Faith, without inward Faith; as if ſalvation were by the letter, and full freedom by the ſpeaker. They will not let to ſay they have begotten ſouls; as if ſalvation were ſimply from their teachings. And thus they ſilence the people under their bands.</p>
            <p>Ah go, go, and tell them ſo, that they ſilence the people, and cannot give them ſpiritual life, but keep them at a diſtance, as a Horſe in a Mill alwaies going round, teaching them repetition and repetition; learning, and yet not come to the knowledge of truth: but <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prove all things,</hi> yet <hi>hold faſt that which is good.</hi> Then lay your heads together, and ye ſhall finde the Miniſters of our time very faulty; They call themſelves <hi>the Miniſters of God,</hi> and ſit in Chriſts place; In the name of the Lord we caſt you forth, and we diſcarge your falſe power, for Chriſt is Adminſtrator, and you are fleſhly and litteral, and have no more power to preach then another man: for Chriſt is the Miniſter of God, and giveth us ſpiritual life to heal our infirmities, and he is our example to walk by: then lay by your covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pride, and follow his example; ſet your ſelves to know God, and then you ſhall find great comfort; for it ſhall ſtir up the gift, which is the beſt teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Miniſters cannot live themſelves, and how ſhould they give life to others? they are full of guilt and ſcandal, and yet they accompt themſelves high Doctors or Miniſters of God, when indeed ye are not ſo, but deceivers of the people; for there is no Miniſter but Chriſt alone: though ye ſtand ſo high in the Pulpits, you muſt come down at the appearing of Chriſt in his power,
<pb facs="tcp:118983:6"/> when all fleſh ſhall bend, both things in Heaven, and things on the Earth, and things under the Earth ſhall all be diſpowered and diſ-throned, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall ſtand but ordination, and that is Chriſt ordayned a Prieſt and a Miniſter for ever: he alone is our ſpiritual teacher, and you Miniſters are worſe then Lay-men for taking upon you that title of Miniſtery, and cannot live free from covetouſneſs which is Idolatry; and you are idolatrous Prieſts, which deceive the ſimple.</p>
            <p>Methinks I could ſtand an hour or two in your idolatrous places to preach as you do, but my conſcience informeth me otherwiſe. Therefore I lay the Ax to the root of your one-legged Pulpits, to cut them down: for you Pulpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayons muſt come down, and ſet upon your low equals. Why ſhould ye ſtand higher then Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that went from place to place diſcipling and teaching? But for ſhame, ſome of you Doctors could ſay your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is <hi>jure Divino,</hi> which is a baſe degree hatched in <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and maintained by a prelatical power, that one alone may be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prem to preach of himſelf in his own tongue, and all the people give audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to hear one infamous man ſpeak by a <hi>primus</hi> or ſupream Authority, whereof none may ſpeak but be ſilenced, whether it be right or wrong; while they declare forth their own Authority, which is the firſt degree of a lying teſtimony: for one tongue cannot fully make a lawful teſtimony. If one Lawyer plead two mens cauſes, he cannot but uſe partiality; neither can any Miniſter plead Gods cauſe and mans cauſe together; it muſt be Chriſt the Mediator, as a Miniſter between God and us. The truths of God ought to be proved by twelve, or by two or three faithful witneſſes, and that is a truth vindicated and proved according to divine juſtice, and not by one mans tongue preaching in a Pulpit, which ſhall ſuddenly be cut down, and Mr. <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitian</hi> ſhall ſtand low among his Fellow-equals, <hi>Babylon</hi> placed ſo high ſhall come down to the Duſt.</p>
            <p>High Doctor, thou counteſt me a fooliſh Shepherd, yet the Lord is with me, to ſhew thee thy folly; for that is truth which is proved by witneſſes, and by the approbation of the Church; for your own tongue is a lye; though ſpeak in a Pulpit, yet ye cannot ſilence the people; for Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith <hi>he heard the ſound of many voices,</hi> and <hi>his witneſſes ſhall have power;</hi> which are they that are within the Covenant, or ſuch as ſhall enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the great Jehovah.</p>
            <p>Ye Doctors of Divinity, as ye call your ſelves, ye have preached long in your own tongue, to keep the World at a diſtance, you have not been buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders but deſtroyers of the Houſe of God: and know ye not the offering of his Temple, but have ſet your ſelves higher then others, exalting your ſelves by your own tongue, as if none could talk of God but Prieſtbitian or Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiry, Prieſts, Dictators, raiſed from <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge?</hi> but without all queſtion, Prieſtinion muſt down.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:7"/>
            <p>Doctor, I acccmpt my ſelf a fool, for I am no good Scribe, neither have I been at Univerſity to learn the ſtammering tongue, and for that we need not much care, unleſs we were to go to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to call in the <hi>Jews,</hi> which ſhall be ſome of every Nation that ſhall be the elect gathered from the four Winds, when the Harveſt ſhall appear which is now at hand, when the Sheep ſhall divide themſelves from the Goats, meaning, the procreation of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall come forth, and ſtand upon their Feet, then the World ſhall be at an end, meaning, it can work its own end no longer; therefore it may be ſaid it is at an end, when they can no longer tread over the two witneſſes, but the Saints on earth ſhall judge and govern them.</p>
            <p>Doctor, I am but a Fool, or a fooliſh Shepherd clothed in ſackcloth 42 Months, from the year 1650. when the ſixth Seal opened the myſtery, to the end of 42 Months, which may be properly taken three years and a halfe, about 54 or 55. God hath given me to look for great deliverance to the Kingdom of the Church, and that Chriſt ſhall raign in power here in <hi>England,</hi> which ſhall be very Oriential to behold, far beyond your learned power; and you ſhall not be Doctor ſpeaker alone, and cannot know any true way, nor live in any ſtable righteouſneſs: for Chriſt the Miniſter of God doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter life and all quickning power, which is the ſubſtance of all, and you cannot do the ſame: therefore lay down your Miniſterial power, and accompt your ſelves as other men; let others ſpeak, and ye ſpeak to them and ſo judge the truth among your ſelves; and throw down the error of one mans tongue. There hath been many Scholars raiſed from <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge;</hi> ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, voluptuous perſons, and yet tolerated by your degrees, and ſo become Pulpitſayons: another ſort have been civil men, though not ſanctified, yet raiſed by the degrees of learning without any Heavenly ſubſtance; others have been raiſed very dunces, neither good Scholars, nor ſpiritually of God and yet have worne long Canonical Gownes, Lawyer-like, whoſe folly was raiſed from thoſe two Fountaines, and much typeth out the Scribes &amp; Phariſees, very proud and ſumptuous, as the <hi>Raven</hi> that ſetteth her Neſt high, to be ſeen and heard afar off; then think they, we are ſecure: and yet their Neſt muſt come down: for the Pulpit-tree having but one Leg, and ſet ſo high, will have a great downfall.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould diſciplying be kept in a Corner ſo high, by one tongue, as one Mr. Speaker?</p>
            <p>Ye Doctors Diffinators, know this, that diſciplying muſt come down among your Fellow-equals, and ſhall be carried by the Feet of the Witneſſes from Sea to Sea, and from one end of the Earth to another. Therefore Chriſt denied himſelf, and would not be Mr. Speaker, ſaying, <hi>If I ſpeak my own words, my teſtimony is not true; there is one that beareth witneſs with me:</hi> and that is tolerable.</p>
            <p>O man, why ſhould thy tongue bear down all, and ſilence all the people,
<pb facs="tcp:118983:7"/> and cannot prove thy ſelf a Miniſter of God, but ſitteth as Scribe in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair?</p>
            <p>Doctor Pulpittian, four things I ſtrike at: Thy Pride, thy Power, thy Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and thy Pulpit.</p>
            <p>Firſt for thy Pride, which is unſeemly for a Diſciple of Chriſt to be proud by ſuch carnal policy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thy Power if it be ſpiritual it is of God; but if a carnal power, it cannot ſtand: for <hi>he will give power to his two faithful Witneſſes</hi> and not to one, though he be never ſo wiſe. Doctor, it is not that Latine tongue that can be good Engliſh, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. calleth it the <hi>ſtammering tongue:</hi> but ye high Prieſts and Lawyers take any courſe to hold up your power. The Univerſities and Innes of Court are fine places for the ſtammering tongue; they be not for the ſimple-hearted; Fools ſhall not come therein; and I am the Fool to tell you ſo. The Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold, thy King commeth riding upon an Aſs.</hi> Now in the time Chriſts power is appearing, a man was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be a Fool or an Aſs then a high Doctor, when their power is ſhaking, and ready to fall, with the reſt of their Pulpittians.</p>
            <p>Doctor, the third thing I ſtrike at, is thy calling. Art thou called of God? then ſhew thy aſſent: if it be of God, it is not from thoſe two high places, but from a heavenly aſſent, Divinalligy of it is from Chriſt, and that is a true cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. But I find your calling is from men, wich cannot be a Divine calling but hatched by the learned Dictators, which is not from the Divine nature, neither doth it ſavour of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but is derived from learned Art and Skill, very tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional; and when it goeth down, we ſhall have a new Government on the earth, which I ſuppoſe wil be betwixt 50. or 57. or ſooner that your pulpits wil down.</p>
            <p>Farther, To vindicate thy Calling, thou ſayeſt thou art the Miniſter of God, ſo wiſe, who may gainſay it? but <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith. <hi>There is more hope of a fool, then of him that is wiſe in his own conceit.</hi> If thou beeſt the Miniſter of God, then Chriſt muſt loſe his place, or thou ſhalt loſe thine; for none can ſay I am a Miniſter of God, without he be ſent of him, ſaying, <hi>Go or go tell them of my reſurrection.</hi> I doubt you will hardly prove any ſuch calling; yet we finde Chriſt was ſent; God he ſent his Son in the ſimilitude of ſinful fleſh once for all, as the Miniſter of eternal life: then why ſhould men hang upon Doctor Speakers, that have learned their skill from <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye Pulpitſayans muſt down; one witneſs cannot be tolerated, for he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to the twelve Apoſtles: and <hi>David</hi> calleth us, <hi>the Ends of the Earth</hi> that God will appear to; <hi>Where two or three are met in my name, I will be in the midſt of them:</hi> which doth debarre one mans ſpeakal tongue: for Chriſt is Divine of himſelf, and man is to be joyntly as one of the Brethren, and ſhall plead for righteouſneſs among the reſt, and to live by the teachings of the Holy Ghoſt, without Dictators or cunning deceivers. And let all the
<pb facs="tcp:118983:8"/> Doctors, high Prieſts, and Prelates know, they are but as other men, and have the ſame infirmities, not able to ſtand; then no high Prieſt or Miniſter, but faylable. Then let us all talk together of the goodneſs of the Lord, and what he hath done for our Souls, acknowledging our ſins one to another, and pray for one another, and give to one another the right hand of Fellowſhip, which will be a ſweet ſavour of goodneſs, to laud the Lord together.</p>
            <p>Doctor, I know none but Chriſts Diſciples that were tolerated to preach, and not any but ſuch as he ſaid unto, <hi>Go and learn all the Nations, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them in the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt,</hi> Mat. 28. he appeared to the two <hi>Maries,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Go;</hi> which was a lawfuller calling then any you can ſhew: and he gave ſome of his Diſciples gifts of healing, which you have not received.</p>
            <p>Doctor, one mans tongue cannot comparmiſe nor comprehend the full truth of God: as the Church may do by many voyces and witneſſes: if Chriſt himſelf the eternal Prieſt denyed himſelf from his own power of ſpeaking, how ought you to be cautelous of ſpeaking your own words, though in a Pulpit?</p>
            <p>I marvel how Pulpits firſt came up; they be much a kin to your Fonts, where ye diſciple Babes in Clouts, which is as a Monſter that ſhall never come to perfection.</p>
            <p>There be many things more that I may tell you of; <hi>Malachy</hi> 3. ſaith, <hi>Bring the Tythes into my ſtore-houſe:</hi> as if by an illuſion he ſhould ſay, For the Blind, the Lame, the Fatherleſs, the Widow, and the Aged, to relieve the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that men might be eaſed of Collection to the Poor in every Pariſh, and for all ſuch as want: And you Pulpit-men work with your hands as others do, for you are almoſt at the end of your period, having ſo much of the Letter, and ſo much example of Chriſt, that I wonder with <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Who hath bewitched you, that you do not obey the truth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye Doctors are carried away from Chriſt by Self-ends and perſonal intereſt, as great Tythes, which is utterly unlawful for them that call themſelves Miniſters of God, and yet rob his Store-houſe, and commit Sacriledge againſt God.</p>
            <p>Under the Law, the order of Gods Houſe was changed by the Prieſts, and the Prophets reproved them for it: under whoſe reproach ye Doctors and Miniſters lye to this day, in that ye rob God of his intereſt. <hi>Bring the Tythes into my Store-houſe:</hi> for now I reprove you under the teſtimony of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>There was a Treaſury in the time of the Apoſtles and Chriſt, which the people miniſtred unto, and brought in their gifts, conſecrating their love to Gods houſe, as <hi>Joanah</hi> and <hi>Suſanna</hi> miniſtred of their ſubſtance to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, and the Widow brought in her mite, which was received with great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation: which way of Gods worſhip you and the Biſhops have ſtrangled
<pb facs="tcp:118983:8"/> Gods Houſe, and got thoſe priviledges into your own hands.</p>
            <p>Again, I muſt tell you both Miniſter and People, impropriations would make the poor of ſuch places merry, if they might or could have their right given them: but we have ſo many devouring Foxes have ſtoln them away, and you have not pleaded for them in the Pulpits, but you falſly keep thoſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits to your ſelves; ye blind guides of the people, that make clean the outſide, and the inſide is full of putrification.</p>
            <p>Theſe Pulpitians have ſpoyled the Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> you have been one of the Hornes of Oppreſſion: otherwiſe we might have had the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Chriſt ſet up before now; which is by Four and Twenty, as we may call Governallity, which is Governation, A Parliament of Four and Twenty, which ſhould be for commonality: but you have ſtood ſo high in your Pulpits, that the ſilly World believeth that your Pulpits were ordained of Chriſt; which were nothing ſo, but aroſe from Biſhops Deanes, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, Deacons, or Doctors of Divinity as ye call them, men of low deſcent, yet raiſed from thoſe two Fountaines <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> pethy places for learning of the ſtammering tongue.</p>
            <p>Chriſt gave gifts of learning, which was not to one, but to more then one; as if he ſhould ſay, Let no man ſilence the people, as he ſaid, <hi>John was a burning and a ſhining Light;</hi> but I have greater witneſſes then that of <hi>John,</hi> for the work to finiſh: ſo that one mans tongue ſhall not ſtand, but the talking of witneſſes ſhall manifeſt every truth; for, Pulpittian, Chriſt queſtioneth thy Authority: thy People ſhall ſpeak and thou muſt anſwer, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the truth cannot be eſtabliſhed without much trouble, and many witneſſes; which produceth the grand voyce of the Church.</p>
            <p>And therefore ye Taskmaſters, down with your Hour-glaſſes; many words in your own tongue cannot ſatisfie the people, neither can you make out truth by your own tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noah</hi> was a Preacher of righteouſneſs, but not in a Pulpit; and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> preached forth Faith; <hi>he believed, and it was counted for him for righteouſneſs.</hi> The good life of thoſe two Fathers preached righteouſneſs to the people, and ſo ſhould yours be to act in righteouſneſs without partiality of the tongue.</p>
            <p>It is not the hearing nor the preaching, but the doing of righteouſneſs: for to enquire the way and not to walk in it, is a vain thing,</p>
            <p>We ought all to live up to God in truth, and that is the beſt teaching; To diſciply and diſtinguiſh truths is good learning, and the beſt preaching to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the things of conſcience by the grand power of the Church, and not to reſt upon the mouth of one teacher: neither do I know any Miniſter after the fleſh, but like Miniſter, like People, all full of frailty; then how canſt thou be a teacher, and art but equal to other men in ſin and ſenſuallity? it is the Sheerds of Gods free mercy, that redeemeth thee as well as others.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:9"/>
            <p>What is the Univerſity more then any other place? your Latine tongue is is but an empty thing; it muſt be onely the Divine power that keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thy ſoul alive, and cauſeth thee and me to live; which is above any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal power: neither can godlineſs be learned; it is from the Miniſterial power of Chriſt, and from the gift of God, and not by the hearing of faith: but thou muſt have a perſonal faith of thine own, and to prove thy ſelf, and lay open thy ſelf to the Church, and <hi>let thy moderation be known to</hi> God, and openly to the people, and pray for one another to Chriſt thy Miniſter, for <hi>by him we have boldneſs to the Throne of grace,</hi> and are made capable of his Miniſtery; which cannot be done by any fleſhly Prieſt, which is but as all other men, though he may ſmooth up the people as if he were the Miniſter of God, and ſo commit Blaſphemy againſt the holy Ghoſt, taking away Chriſts Authority, making themſelves Pulpittians, to tye up the conſciences of ſuch as follow them, as if they had full power given them of God.</p>
            <p>Ye Doctors and Miniſters, ye muſt fall ſome degrees worſe then your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Biſhops; the light of the Lord ſhall ſo cleerly uſher in, that you ſhall be diſcovered, and Chriſt ſhall be chiefe Speaker to his flock; one Prieſt, one People; one Shepherd, one Sheep of the elect; <hi>Abraham</hi> called and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by Chriſt, and not by mens teaching.</p>
            <p>For Mr. Speaker, Doctor of tongues, you may ſay, What, do we ſtand for a Cypher? Yes: for Chriſt is all our teacher, and you Miniſters lye under the vail as well as others.</p>
            <p>Therefore (Miniſter) lay down thy falſe power, and deceive the people no longer, and know thy ſelf as low as others, and much inferiour to Chriſt. Oh take not away his Divine Authority, which properly belongeth to the Son of God. Chriſt he preacheth continually to them that are neer, and to them afar off: he preacheth to every Kindred, Tongue, Language, and Nation; he ſaith, <hi>My Sheep hear my voyce;</hi> not <hi>your Sheep;</hi> he ſaith, <hi>My Diſciples keep my ſayings,</hi> not <hi>your ſayings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my part, I accompt all you Pulpittians to be but falſe Chriſts; yet I diſparage not the gift of godlineſs in you, but I adhere to any thing that is good in you. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>They ſhall come in my Name, and decieve the People.</hi> And truly ye Miniſters and high Doctors muſt needs be the men, for you call your ſelves the Miniſters of God ſtanding in the high place, and alas ye are no more then lay-men that never were at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge:</hi> you be men of infirmity as others be, and therefore your power will fall, and cannot ſtand.</p>
            <p>O General, O Parliament, O People, why do you commit error againſt God and his Chriſt, to follow after fained lovers, which are but Miniſters of the letter, and have not the gifts of healing, neither are they ſent? for it is Chriſt that miniſtreth the gift to all, &amp; keepeth all alive by a power from above;
<pb facs="tcp:118983:9"/> and every perſon that is godly, ſhall have a perſonal power in himſelf from Chriſt to ſtand upon his Feet, without a Pulpit-preacher: for man cannot preach of himſelf, except he was ſent of Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Go, or go forth,</hi> as he ſaid to his Diſciples. But now in our dayes God hath appeared to us by his Sonne, and no other: and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If I go from you, I will ſend you the Comforter, that ſhall teach you in all truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>What ſhall he teach the Parſons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, as well as the People: for Miniſter and People ſhall be but Sheep in his Fold; for Chriſt is the high Prieſt; <hi>his Lips ſhall preſerve knowledge; ye ſhall all know me from the greateſt to the leaſt;</hi> there muſt be a perſonal knowing of God by faith, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Noah lived and walked with God, and it was accounted to them for righteouſneſs;</hi> every degree, from the Doctor to the People, ſhall know God, and ſtand upon their Feet, without a Preacher, whoſe breath is in their Noſtrils: ſilly Guides, not able to ſtand of themſelves, neither can they Doctor up others, but may go teach our Children of ſeven years old.</p>
            <p>I am but a Fool to ſpeak that which no man hath declared; but I can have no reſt for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake, nor give my ſelf any reſt, until I ſee the work of God accompliſhed in the Earth, which is the procreation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that ſhall come forth and ſtand upon their Feet.</p>
            <p>Army, Army, O Arm of the Lord Almighty, Army ſhall ſtand upon their Feet, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 37. which I ſuppoſe will be within four or five years after 1650. to the admiration of the World.</p>
            <p>Ye Miniſters and Doctors Definators, ye would fain hold up your high places, but truly your Temple muſt fall; for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>There ſhall not be one Stone left upon another, that ſhall not be thrown down:</hi> for your Worldly power will be at an end, when Chriſt the great Shepherd ſhall call forth his Flock to ſtand upon their Feet, and live without your Declarations; when all men ſhall declare out of the gift, and not by the letter, to ſpeak the things they have received of God, and ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe your teachers that are not ſent of God, but be End-workers and Mony-merchants, that ſhall be diſſolved and caſt out of the Temple as Mony-changers; for God will ſet up a diſciplying, when your power lyeth low as Doctor <hi>Hill</hi>'s Bones, and we may ſay with the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel, Blow Wind, and ſhake the four quarters of the Earth, to raiſe thoſe dry Bones, that have been very dry ſo long,</hi> that they come up in the Valley of Jeſus Chriſt: for he ſhall ſit to judge the Heathen round about. Put in the Sickle, the Harveſt is ripe, the Wine-preſs overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; multitudes, multitudes ſhall uſher in, they ſhall be a willing People in the day of Gods power: but all ye Doctors are ſo high and juſtitious, that ye keep Chriſt off from his regal power and Authority;
<pb facs="tcp:118983:10"/> therefore ye ſhall fall with reproach under Armegiddon. Oh Arme, Arme, Arme of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Finally, Doctor, you ſtand in Chriſts place. Man may ſpeak out his judgement, that another may anſwer, and Chriſt he miniſtreth to all: every truth muſt be proved affirmatively, but not by one mans tongue; and you ſhall be called to account by the grand Church: for the Prophet <hi>John</hi> ſaith, There ſhall be Lightning, Thundering, Voyces and Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Light of the Lord appeares, and ſhall break down the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he will Thunder forth Juſtice, Judgement, and Equity in the Earth, by a perſonal power of Saints under him. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells you ſo, that <hi>the Saints muſt judge the World,</hi> and you the Angels of the Churches too.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he will appear by many Voyces, that ſhall give ſentence and decide every truth.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he will appear by Witneſſes, which ſhall extinguiſh one mans tongue: for the mouth of two or three witneſſes ſhall be an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, and the many Voyces ſhall ſwallow up your Miniſterial Voyce.</p>
            <p>Theſe two witneſſes ſhall have power in the dayes of their Propheſie to turn the waters into blood ſo often as they will; that is, to declare forth the bloody condition of blood-thirſty perſons; which you dare not do, for loſing your impropriated Parſonages.</p>
            <p>Theſe Witneſſes ſhall have power to ſhut Heaven gates ſo often as they will, that it rain not. It is not meant the imperial Heaven of Heavens; but it is meant, they ſhall ſhut the gates of the heavenly and viſible Kingdom here below, that none ſhall enter in to raigne in that pure State, but ſuch as ſhall be approved Members of that glorious <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above.</p>
            <p>Theſe Witneſſes ſhall <hi>have power to ſhut Heaven that i<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rayne</hi> not, that is, twelve; it ſhall not raigne in the dayes of their power, but ſhall be finally ſwallowed up in the Victory of Chriſt: it ſhall not raigne, it and it, it and it, it and it, it and it, it and it, it and it: That is, no outward power ſhall raign in the time of Chriſts power.</p>
            <p>The firſt the firſt thing that ſhall not raigne, is Earthly King and Grace.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that ſhall not raigne, is Lord and Protector.</p>
            <p>The third thing that ſhall not raigne, is Power and Excellency of Man.</p>
            <p>The fourth thing that ſhall not raigne, is Worſhip and Honor.</p>
            <p>The fifth thing that ſhall not raign, is Highneſs and Greatneſs of Men.</p>
            <p>The ſixth thing that ſhall not raigne, is Prieſt and Lawyer: for
<pb facs="tcp:118983:10"/> Chriſt will ſit upon the backs of all thoſe, and be exalted by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the people: multitudes, multitudes ſhall ſtand upon Angella: Chriſt muſt raign by his Saints till he hath put all Authority and power under his Feet, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>The Feet of the two Witneſſes ſhall tread in pieces the Dragons tail; as Chriſt broke his head, ſo they ſhall bruiſe his heel: for the Antitype of Satans Kingdom muſt fall and periſh under the power of Army Gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
            <p>O Army, Army, Arme of the Lord, he will create a defence upon thy Walls and Bulworks: They ſhall have power to ſhut Heaven that it rain not, that is, they ſhall ſilence all the powers, and the Angels of your Churches, that is, by a new diſciplying power that ſhall put down the raigning power of ſuch as have raigned over his power: though they may make an attempt againſt the holy City, yet fire muſt come down from Heaven and deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Any inſtrument framed againſt the power of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhall not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; none ſhall raigne in this Kingdom but the faithful Witneſſes of Chriſt called and choſen.</p>
            <p>Theſe Witneſſes are ſaid to be two, though many in number; yet two is the leaſt number, which maketh one mans teſtimony void, and of none effect.</p>
            <p>Ye great and high Doctors, and all ye Legators, what will become of your Courts and infamous Colledges? I ſuppoſe in ſhort time they will ſtand like old <hi>Pauls,</hi> or the Barn of <hi>Westminster,</hi> without any trading; very infamous, yet borne up with Crutches, whoſe conſtellations will fail, and all your Prieſtly powers which have raigned ſo long over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for there is one King, one Lord, one High-Prieſt, and one Prophet, that ſhall put down every power.</p>
            <p>High and lofty Doctors, that ha<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e got ſo many hundreds a year in your hands, and yet are commanded to bring your Tythes into Gods Store-houſe, and not into your own houſes; you have kept the people under bondage, which God will now ſet at liberty, when your Miniſtery is down: yet the people ſhall bring the tenth of their ſubſtance into Gods Store-houſe, as their Father <hi>Abraham</hi> did, which ſhall ſhame your doings that are not good. He ſaith, <hi>You go to your Cieled Houſes, but my Houſe lyeth deſolate:</hi> and ye rob Gods Houſe of the benefits, and come not in at the Door, but clime up ſome <hi>other way,</hi> which is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the Door, the Truth, the Life,</hi> and ye injoy all things of my Father; and thoſe benefits of Tythes you cannot injoy to your ſelves, for they be proper to the Widow, the Fatherleſs, the Stranger, the Blind, and the Lame, and to be brought into the Store-houſe;
<pb facs="tcp:118983:11"/> for Collection and hoſpitality to thoſe that want. But in this I finde the Prieſts do omit, and commit Sacriledge, againſt the Order of Gods houſe.</p>
            <p>Ye Doctors, ſee and wonder, the Lord hath appeared in me, that I ſhould be to you as a fooliſh Shepherd, to tell you of folly; ſometimes in the night, when my Body ſlept, yet my ſpirit was awake, and heard as it had been Voyces, both in the night and alſo on the day; which cauſed me to write, when he declared unto me the things that ſhould ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to paſs, by ſo many dark and ſpiritual appearances: which are hideous to men, yet known to me, as one born in due time.</p>
            <p>Doctor High-Prieſt, you muſt ſtoop at ordination, Chriſt was an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Miniſter, ſo was not you; he was ſent of his Father. Now if you can prove your ſelves ordained Minſters, then you may put Chriſt out of his place.</p>
            <p>You are of the Stepmother or Bondwoman, and came not in at the Door, which is not according to ordination, but by way of impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, or a taking Chriſts place upon your ſelves; and ſet your ſelves in high places, as Miniſters of God, though not ordained, yet you take upon you the place of Chriſt, and declare your ſelves Paſtors to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and yet not able to feed your ſelves.</p>
            <p>O ſilly Shepherds, know aſſuredly, there is but one Paſtor, and that is Chriſt alone; he is <hi>Pastor unus, Pastor varius, Pastor magnus,</hi> and <hi>Pastor function:</hi> he is the great <hi>Shepherd and Biſhop of our ſouls;</hi> he is our book of remembrance; he is the eternal word, without any Letter-teachers.</p>
            <p>It's a great ſhame that men live more by the teachings of men, then they do by the teachings of the Sonne of God, which teacheth us in all things.</p>
            <p>Then down with all your Letter-teachers, that are as Lawyers, that ſtudy wiſdom by art by policy, by learning and skill to deceive them of weak underſtanding <hi>Mal</hi> 3. ſaith, There was <hi>a Book of Remembrance</hi> opened, and <hi>they talked often together;</hi> which was the beſt teaching. So that, Voyces and Witneſſes ſhall be heard in the room of the Prieſts: for ye muſt lay down your Prieſtly power; ye muſt deny your ſelves, and declare Chriſt to be all in all, that he may be Prieſt &amp; King over all: but ye have ſtood ſo long as Vice-admiral over all in your Pulpits, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering over the People, to keep them under your rule.</p>
            <p>Doctor, thou canſt not truly preach Chriſt, till thou throweſt all down at his Feet: and whatever thou beeſt, thou muſt throw down thy own ſelf-power.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>What a Minister, and throw-down his power?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, why not? for how canſt thou royally preach Chriſt and declare thy ſelf a Miniſter of God, and yet walke after the cuſtome of the World? I ſay, If thou liveſt not after the example of Chriſt, thou art a Miniſter of ſinne, and thy life doth not teach others; then thou maiſt <hi>preach to others, and be a cast-away thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas poor fleſhly man, thou teacheſt the Letter, and yet art ignorant of the truth; thou haſt ſet thy ſelf high in a ſay-Pulpit, to ſpeak great things in a ſeenal way of repetitions, ſpeaking many things to pleaſe the people.</p>
            <p>Ye be ſubtil Sophiſters, men-pleaſers, and ſelf-ſeekers, that can derive themſelves into many formes, contrary to the truth of God, by ſetting up Sub-ordination in the place of Ordination, to ſet themſelves higher then Chriſt: And in that they are made equal with him; for <hi>he was made a little lower then the Angel,</hi> meaning the Angels of your Churches, that ſtill keep him upon the Croſs, and crucifie his power.</p>
            <p>Chriſt was ordained Miniſter of God, but ye ordained your ſelves.</p>
            <p>I can give a relation of one within the County of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> a Minſter called Mr. <hi>Male,</hi> as I underſtand, doth ordaine Miniſters, and that ſome petty Miniſters have come many Miles to be ordained of him: which is intolerable: I wonder his heels are not pictured upwards.</p>
            <p>Thus they may do, though not by Lawful means. But be you ſure, all ſub-powers muſt down, as things in Heaven, and things on Earth, and things under the Earth, muſt bow at the name of Jeſus. He is the Prince of Peace, and Prince of Power: the Lord ſhall be exalted in all the Earth, and your powers ſhall come down as low as dry Bones.</p>
            <p>Ye high Prieſts, know this, that your ſtate is failable for as you have cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down the Biſhop and his Surplis, ſo now the Witneſſes ſhall cry down with your Pulpits and your Fonts: you are ſpiritual high in your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, full of pride, ſedition, and covetouſneſs, ſelf-ſeeking, full of envy and bitterneſs; in that ye differ not from the general world, &amp; yet you can ſay you are the Miniſters of God, &amp; yet not walk after the example of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This that I declare, is called <hi>your Funeral-Sermon,</hi> or wind-up, for ye ſhall be eclipſed by the bright appearings of the Lord.</p>
            <p>This eclipſe took its firſt entrance in the year 1650. which ſhall cauſe the greateſt earth-quake that ever was ſince the creation; and the power of it ſhall decline towards the fourth or fifth yeer after 50. here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctors, what will ye do when your Tythes fail, and your Miniſtery fails, &amp; your new-Moons and Sabbaths fail? then it ſhall be to you as the mourning of <hi>Hadadrimmon,</hi> or a deſtructive time, when ye ſhall have no audience or accommodation of the people; for every one ſhall have a perſonal power put in them, to ſtand alone, without Preachers. They ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:118983:12"/> be ſo inherently taught of God, that the Miniſter ſhall ſay no more to them, Know the Lord; for they ſhall all be Prophets inwardly, and ſhall ſtand by a perſonal faith, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> did in fulneſs of Spirit: for the Lord ſaith, <hi>In the laſt dayes I will pour out my Spirit upon all fleſh, and my ſervants and hand-maids ſhall propheſie;</hi> When ye Miniſters may ſay, We are Vine-dreſſers and Husbandmen, to till the waſte Commons; for our weekly Sabbaths are changed into one Sabbath; once a year we ſhall go up to worſhip the Lord, and to keep a Feaſt of Tabernacles, which is a true Sabbath according to Chriſts Reſurrection, to keep a good conſcience, which is a Feaſt in the heart of the Creature, and that is the beſt Sabbath, to live in all righteouſneſs every day, which is a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</p>
            <p>And though the Jew have have loſt his new-Moon, and thou O Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile thy new-Moon, yet thou ſhalt remember the Lord, and once a year conſecrate thy gift to him, and keep a new Sabbath by an offering to God in his new Covenant, to worſhip him with all thy ſubſtance: and then it will appear that thou art one of the new Sabbath. Thou muſt deny thy ſelf-ends, and all ſiniſter engagements, and ſo betroth thy ſelf unto God in righteouſneſs, to covenant with him according to the new-Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Though the Conſtellations may fail, yet his Sabbath-Ordinance ſhall ſtand, it ſhall not be diſannulled: <hi>Heaven and Earth may paſs away, but not one jot or tittle of his word ſhall fail.</hi> For Chriſt is the word of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; and in him we ſhall have reſt, if we enter into Covenant, and that is to acknowledge him by a new Sabbath: for <hi>in thoſe dayes, and at that time, ſaith the Lord, I will make with them a new Covenant, not according to the old; for this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make, never to turn from them,</hi> or take away the Ordinance of Sabbath from them,</p>
            <p>Yet the Lord ſaith, <hi>I hate your Sabbaths, becauſe your hands are full of blood.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Ye keep Sabbaths to your ſelves, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs my holy day. <hi>Once a year thou ſhalt come up to keep a Feaſt of Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles; and all that will not come to the worſhip of Jeruſalem, ſhall have no rain,</hi> or raigning power in this new Sabbath of reſt.</p>
            <p>Silly Prieſt, I queſtion not, though thy Sabbath be taken away: for Chriſt is thy eternal Sabbath, and thou ſhalt worſhip him according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> for all your ſubordinances ſhall ſtoop at ordination: your Sabbaths ſhall change into one Sabbath. <hi>If thou wilt walk in my wayes, and do that I command thee this day, then thou ſhalt ride upon the high places of the Earth;</hi> that is, whoever ſhall Covenant to this new Sabbath, ſhall enjoy all the promiſes, the Lord ſaith, <hi>I will dwell in you, and ye in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miniſters, your Sabbaths are failable, therefore they be called <hi>your Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118983:12"/> by illuſion, as if he ſhould ſay, If ye keep a day, keep it to me: for you obſerve dayes, and do no righteouſneſs; therefore your new Moons and Sabbaths ſhall change and be taken away: for <hi>I will make a new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with them, ſaith the Lord, not according to the old; but this ſhall be my Covenant, never to turn from them</hi> that truely Covenant to me: ſaying, <hi>I will betroth thee unto me in mercy and loving kindneſs, and thou ſhalt know the Lord: for my counſel ſhall ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctor, the taking away your Sabbath ſhall cauſe the Lords Sabbath to ſhine out more clear; for ye have changed my Ordinances, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>Therefore the Land is curſed with a curſe;</hi> and your moonorital Sabbaths ſhall change: if ye keep one day, keep it to me, ſaith the Lord. So that we ought to keep every day as a Sabbath once a year, to make out our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, which is Eaſter-day, and the ſix dayes before it: for every year ſhall be called as a Sabbath-day, and ſo from year to year ye ſhall keep my Sabbath Ordinances, and live in them that is, from year to year ye muſt come to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> worſhip, <hi>Zachary</hi> 14. Chriſt preached every where, and made every day a Sabbath.</p>
            <p>It is not for thee and me to keep a day once a Week, and walk contrary to God in all the reſt. If ye keep a day, keep it to me; and keep every day as a Sabbath.</p>
            <p>One reaſon is, ye make the ſeventh day a Cloak for your ſinne, to uſe holineſs for your own turn; ſo did the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law, and Chriſt cut off their Sabbath, and ſo he will yours, ſo that you ſhall not inſult over them, nor they over you: for, ſaith he, <hi>I hate your new Moons, and your Sabbaths.</hi> The Lords day ſhould be a reſt betwixt God and thy Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; if Chriſt dwell in thee, thy ſoul is full of light. If ye keep Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with me, I will be your reſting-place: and that is a Sabbath in thy Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Paul ſaith, <hi>ye obſerve dayes, and months; I wonder who hath bewitched you.</hi> Your way of holineſs is as the witcharft of <hi>Endor,</hi> ſubtilly to beguile men, and cauſe them to ſwim in vain conceits, and ſo to hold up your a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations by keeping ſo many Sabbath dayes once a week for your own turnes, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did their ſeventh day, and yet perſecute Chriſt: and therefore it is not for them nor us to obſerve daies, for there is but one Sabbath, and that is the Lord, in whom we ſhall have reſt; and that is to reform our lives, and live in all good conſcience, to walk in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and that is the beſt Sabbath, ſhewing the day of his reſurrection by a newneſs of life.</p>
            <p>And at the appearing of the Lords power, the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> Sabbath are out, by a wonderful dividing of time, called <hi>once a year;</hi> ſo that I finde the whole year is the Lords Sabbath: All the year, you in me, and
<pb facs="tcp:118983:13"/> I in you. Thou ſhalt conſecrate thy ſubſtance to the Lord, which is the ſeventh from the creation, called the ſeventh vial or valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> under which the World ſhall come under judgement, called the Sabbaths Vial, which is that we now live under, called the ſeparate time that God will ſet apart and take to himſelf the great glory of Monarchy, that now ſhall reſume that name to themſelves: and therefore, Prieſt, thou muſt fall with the King and Lord of diſhonor, that the propheſie may be made out, that you may ſay, <hi>I am no more a Prophet, but an Herds-man, or keeper of Cattle;</hi> I am but as other men, no Prieſt, no Miniſter; no Miniſter, then ſilence not the People.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118983:13"/>
            <head>The ſecond PART OF D. Hils Funeral-Sermon, WITH <hi>His Apellation to Priests and People.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By me <hi>Henry Haſſelwood.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>THere be four ſorts of Definators, that may be called the Witch of the world, very ſeenal and ſubtil. I call them not the Witch of <hi>Jezebel,</hi> neither do I call them the Witch of <hi>Endor;</hi> yet I call them the Witch of the earth, in that they uſe their own authority, and pretend fair things, though foul in effect; promoting themſelves by skill and art, making out the authority of the beaſt, and ſo deceive the people. Thoſe are four in number, yet not any of them ſhall remain in authority, for the Witch ſhall be cut off out of the earth, and all that make a lye, and every abominable branch ſhall be found out. The Witch of the world is very ſubtil, and much deceiveth by flatteries and ſeenal Juglings, to ſteal away the peoples appetite, as to delude them with ſmoke, or to puff them up with ſome vain oſtentation: ſubtil Sophiſters, winding themſelves into the form of Chriſt, deceiving the people, denying the power of his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, preaching up themſelves, bewitching the world, and deceive the people. So much for the firſt Definators, that call themſelves Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, and are not. Brethren, I would have every one live up to the teachings of God, without ſecond-hand-teachers; and to walk up to that principle of grace put into them: for ſpiritually we live under the divine power of the Son of God; he is all our teacher, to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118983:14"/> guide us in the way of truth; it is not for man to do it. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Renew in me a right ſpirit:</hi> Pſal. 1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Who knoweth the error of his life?</hi> Who can teach, but Chriſt alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then <hi>let us ſtand in that liberty wherein he hath made us free.</hi> And <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Walk ſo, that you may be judged by the law of liberty.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prove every truth;</hi> that is, by witneſſes. So that no man can preach of himſelf, but Chriſt doth preach all, both neer and afar off, by a ſingular power from God to teach us all things: he ſaith, <hi>I am the way,</hi> walk in it, follow my example, but not the examples of men. The Doctrine is from thence, <hi>That all men and miniſters are but learners, and cannot teach any further then they walk by a good example.</hi> The firſt Reaſon is, It is not words, but works of faith and piety, which is a good example: It is not for a man to ſay, I am a Miniſter, and yet but all words. Look upon the good life, and not upon the profeſſion. The ſecond Reaſon is, Men or Miniſters have no lawful authority to teach: for Chriſt and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt inwardly teacheth; and they are the two Witneſſes by a law inſerted in the conſcience. The third Reaſon is, They cannot teach, in that they cannot prove Ordination. The fourth Reaſon is, That every petty Prieſthood muſt fall, and ſtoop at Chriſts Miniſtery. But ſome ſilly people may object, <hi>Shall we loſe our teachers? better loſe our Chriſt.</hi> And ſo they dote upon a Miniſtery of fleſh. Was not Chriſt the Meſſiah a Miniſter ordained of God? He teacheth, and ſhall ſit upon twelve thrones by a power, and all men &amp; Miniſters muſt come under his teaching, and lay down their Crowns; and the honourable men muſt ſtoop at his Scepter: for he is the Miniſter of God, and no other: for we have had many Teachers, yet none can lead us in the true way. And having ſo great an high-Prieſt, that is able to lead us in all truth, he hath once entred into the Prieſtly Office, and maketh interceſſion to God for us continually. Then why ſhould we lean upon the pettifogging Prieſts, which muſt come down from their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit-Thrones, and ſet up Chriſt upon his throne? For while your Power raigneth, Chriſts power is crucified upon the croſs, and his truth ſuffereth violence. But now he ſhall ſit upon your thrones, and judge the Whoriſh power by a ſeat of juſtice, ſo ordained. And until you all throw down, and make Chriſt the full end and ſcope of all teaching, your Temple will be divided: for you muſt come all to the Law and Teſtimony, which is Chriſt and the Spirit writ as a Law and Teſtimony in our conſciences, which are the two witneſs-bearers to prove every true Chriſtian: for this is a time dividing time; I ſpeak of a new Sabbath, Chriſt in the conſcience, every day, once a yeer continually: I ſpeak of a new Sabbath; old things muſt paſs away,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118983:14"/> and the things that are old muſt change. Brethren, ye ought not to look ſo much upon feigned Teachers of the ſecond hand, feigned lovers, and ſo defile the Chriſtian Marriage, and break your Sabbath-union with Chriſt, to follow Teachers <hi>whoſe breath is in their noſtrils,</hi> and ſhall down at the teſtimony and feet of the two Witneſſes, when all things ſhall be brought upon record, and great <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall come in remembrance, and power ſhall be given to the Saints, as <hi>Daniel, John,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> declareth. Then Doctor look to it, for thou ſhalt be cenſured by the Church: then Kings ſhall throw down, and Lords throw down, and Honours throw down, and Prieſts throw down; we muſt all throw down our Crowns and Dignities, and ſtoop to the firſt dominion. <hi>Thy kingdom come,</hi> whoſe Scepter ſhall not fade away: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very pretended Power framed againſt him, ſhall not proſper. If thou calleſt thy ſelf King, it is high conſpiracie againſt the King of heaven, ſo to pollute his holy name: for he is that one Lord of the whole earth. Now if he be Lord, then thy name Lord muſt down of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: for God will have his Name known thorow all the earth, and before him every knee ſhall bow. Then ſet not up thy ſelf: the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt climb may have the greateſt fall. If thy place be never ſo high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, yet it may be but a left-hand-mercy, or ſuch a priviledge as will decline: and whoever ſtandeth as Lord or King, ſhall fall at the appearing of Chriſts power. And the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, They ſhall fall too that hold them up; that is, he that giveth the name Lord to a man, he ſhall fall by diſhonour: for there ſhall be but one Lord over the earth, and his Name one: for the name of <hi>Baal,</hi> Monarchy ſhall be cut out of the earth, that aſſume to themſelves ſuch high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and pollute his holy Name: it is an intolerable Witchcraft that ſhall be cut out of the earth, that hath ſo long deceived the people, calling fleſhly man Lord, and ſo pollute the name of the holy One of Iſrael, taking his name in vain. He is the Lord of the Creation, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtand up for him, and thy liberty: O Army, Army, arm of the Lord, ſtand up; for it is given thee, That every Power ſhall periſh under thee. <hi>Army-giddon,</hi> valley of deſtruction, or a deſtructive ſword ſhall riſe, that God will fourbiſh againſt all the powers, none excepted: but his Divine power ſhall ſtand, that ſhall govern under him: his power ſhall raign in all places; and ſo far as they keep up the Lords honour, they ſhall ſtand with proſperity. But your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable-men muſt fall: though they ſet their names as high as heaven, yet they ſhall come down: for the Lord will ſet on fire the four ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which are not the skies, as ſilly men teach, but it is that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly power that hath raigned ſo long, and ſhall now burn at his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118983:15"/> bright appearing, and ſhall expel all the Witchcraft of the world. Secondly, the general world muſt change its courſe, by a more ſweet comply of Government, and to lay by their outward Idolatry. The third element that ſhall burn, is the proud waters <hi>Euphrates,</hi> ſeven ſtreams of powers ſhall dry up: all the Egyptian powers ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; and no power ſhall ſtand, but that of the Son of God. The fourth element that ſhall burn, is the Moon and Stars. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>When the light ſhineth from the eaſt to the west, then the power of the Son of man is nigh at hand.</hi> You know, when the Sun appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in its brightneſs, the Moon and Stars muſt give place to that light, and it onely raigneth over them: ſo Doctors, Miniſters, and Churches, your lights ſhall go out at his appearing, and all your Moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norical powers ſhall be extinguiſhed, and all the Stars called Miniſters ſhall loſe their borrowed lights; when every one ſhall acknowledge Chriſt to be their Miniſter, and live under their own vine. So much for the four Elements, called the four Conſtellations, which is the Church-power, or otherwiſe called Moon and Stars, that ſhall fail at his bright appearing, that the glory of the Son of God may appear from on high, and that all may be reconciled to his light, declaring him to be King, Lord, Prieſt, and Prophet, the onely called Miniſter of God, before whom every Miniſtery ſhall ceaſe; onely pleading for truth ſhall hold, with prayer and mourning among all Chriſtians, called the great mourning of all the families of the earth, every fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily apart: when the brightneſs of the Son of God appeareth, it ſhall be as the mourning in <hi>Hadadrimmon,</hi> when there ſhall be trembling and quaking, as the Prophets did in their times of danger; when there ſhall be a great ſhaking, that men ſhall ſhake, &amp; Miniſters ſhake, and every power ſhake, truely then it behoveth every one to quake and tremble: for the Lord will terribly ſhake the earth: the mighty men ſhall fall, &amp; the honorable men ſhall throw down their Honors, and ſhall deny their high Titles of Grace and Worſhip: for all their ſeenal Witchcrafts ſhall be cut out of the earth, and every Witch that deceiveth the people: every Soothſayer ſhall be found out, and every Sorcerer that deceiveth: for all things ſhall be proved upon the Sanctuary: thou ſhalt not worſhip any graven image, which is but an earthly man, to fall down and worſhip before him: thou ſhalt worſhip God, and him alone, and not man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, though living in honour, yet ſhall periſh as the beaſts from his preſence, as contemptible.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118983:15"/>
            <p>IT hath always been, that wicked <hi>Hamans</hi> have ruled over the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God: they be called <hi>Gog,</hi> or <hi>Haman-Gog,</hi> that ſhall be brought under; and ſo low, that they ſhall not act as they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly done. What have your Pulpittians been all along, but as a Gallows to hang up <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s. Though I do not ſay all Miniſters are <hi>Hamans,</hi> yet ſome of that ſtrain have been cruel men called Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: and for the moſt part you Prieſts are much like the generation that fell before <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo proud, that God in his jealouſie threw them down. They were called the Angels that fell, and Royally petype out Miniſters, that <hi>John</hi> calleth the Angels of the Churches, or the Stars that muſt fall, that have ſtood ſo long in the holy place of Chriſt, and now ſhall be bound down with the world, under the name and notion of the worldly kingdom, that ſhall ſuddenly be bound down for one thouſand yeers. When Chriſts power ſhall raign, then Satan and his kingdom ſhall be bound, ſaid to be <hi>Haman-Gog,</hi> that ſhall have no more power to aſſail and afflict the people of Chriſt; when the perſecuting power is taken off, when the Saints ſhall ſit and judge the Miniſters which hold up the power of the Beaſt, which ſtand ſo high as Lord Speaker, to ſilence the people. Ye Miniſters are called the abomination ſitting in the holy place, as Mediators betwixt God and men: ſo high, in the place of Chriſt, and therefore <hi>Capernaum</hi> exalted ſo high ſhall come down as lowe as dry bones: for <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Haman-Gog</hi>'s bones ſhall be gathered together, and ſo be buried by the number of ſeven yeers, that their weapons and power ſhall have an end. Now to accompliſh this prophecie, look in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. he ſpeaketh of burning their weapons, burying of their bones; which we hope will be in ſome ſhort time after 1650. or before 1657. in our Nation. We cannot predict the full accompliſhment, or make out a full diſcovery of the great deſigne he hath to do, or when it ſhall fully end: yet I hope the time is at hand: for a ſhort work will the Lord make upon earth, to redeem thoſe dry bones that have been very dry, poor Witneſſes of Chriſt killed and troden down by your Prieſtly power: falſe Chriſts, ſecond-hand Teachers of the letter, but can give no ſpiritual life, and yet call your ſelves Miniſters of God, you ſhall fall with great rebuke; one witneſs of Chriſt ſhall chaſe a thouſand of you, and two witneſſes ſhall put ten thouſand of you to flight. O down with your falſe power: for Chriſt Jeſus will redeem Iſrael out of your hands. The two Witneſſes plead ſhall bring down your power as lowe as Doctor <hi>Hill</hi>'s bones: for the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall live without your teachings, and ſhall ſtand upon their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118983:16"/> feet a mighty Army. O Arm of the Lord, every Power ſhall periſh under thee. <hi>Object.</hi> Doth Chriſt need Miniſters? then where is his power, or divine light, or ſpiritual appearances? Doth he not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in all, and teach all by a ſpiritual teaching, which is far higher then all fleſhly teachers can do? I am aſhamed to hear your Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to ſay ye are his Miniſters: then ye may go and teach him what to do. The Heavens preach, the Stars preach, and the Creatures preach, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. but what is this to the preaching of God in his power? Chriſt Jeſus is in the mount, and preacheth to all things. <hi>John</hi> ſaith he is the Angel fleeing in the midſt of heaven, and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the everlaſting Goſpel to every kindred, language, and nation: then what need we have ſo many Preachers? When Chriſt preacheth to all, he ſilenceth the tongues of men and Angels. Chriſt is upon the mount, and it cleft aſunder, ſhewing that every preaching power ſhall break and diſſolve. Now the Angel he preacheth in power: Chriſt Jeſus is the Angel of the Covenant, therefore let all the earth be ſilent: he will make all quiet before him: it is he alone that ſhall ſtill the rage of the ſea, and will quiet mens ſpirits, when they ſhall yield the power of preaching into his hand, when Miniſters ſhall ſtrive no more for their own power. He is the onely preacher. When he ſtood upon mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> it cleft in ſunder: ſo ſhall every preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power diſſolve before him. He is the preacher of light and life: but ye Diviners, Soothſayers, and Flatterers, ye call your ſelvs prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: what need that? There is but one preacher; he ſtandeth on the mount. Chriſt he ſhall put all rule and all authority under his feet: he leadeth us by his holy Spirit, that ſhall guide us in all truth. The Creatures may preach, yet not declare forth the inviſible power of God, for that is proper to Chriſt alone, to preach forth the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. Therefore ſtop your mouthes, ye Prieſts: for <hi>every one ſhall be taught of God, from the greteaſt to the leaſt;</hi> even ye high Doctors muſt come under the teachings of the Son of God: he is the Day-ſtar that dawneth from on high. If ever thou wilt ſee life, that ſpiritual life muſt be from him, to transform thee into the likeneſs of him: for the way of all mens teachings ſhall burn up with their wood and ſtraw, and every untempered thing which holds up the abomination that makes deſolation. And truely Miniſters are to blame in this thing of diſcipline. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.10. that principalities and powers in high places ought to be approved by the Church, that is, to put forth Queries of Scripture, and to quire out every truth by witneſſes: for every viſion ſhall fail at the beatifical viſion. Ye ſons of <hi>Ai</hi> muſt down: it is not any viſible power that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118983:16"/> can ſtand before the inviſible; nor any created power ſtand before the Ordained and Created Miniſter of God. Ye ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> muſt throw down: though you have been Legators ſo long, yet now there is an Alligator that teacheth us all things, by his bright appearing, far higher then you can elevate. It is not your literal teachings, but it is the inviſible teachings of the Son of God, that maketh wiſe to ſalvation. Call not thy ſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt, for he is a Miniſter of himſelf. Therefore lay down thy power: for he teacheth us in all truth. We and our predeceſſors have been taught by you, and ſuch as have called themſelves Lord Biſhops: horrible names, and intolerable, to call themſelves Lords. And you Prieſts call your ſelvs Miniſters of Chriſt, yet you are but of that ſpawn of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> that ſhall dry up, with thy Lord Biſhop, Lord of folly. Thoſe, and ſuch as you be, have nuzled up the people to thie day. But now God will teach his people to ſtand and live without your Lordly power. Your Biſhops are fallen, and you muſt fall under contempt, for ſitting in the holy place as Miniſters or falſe Chriſts, to deceive and ſeduce the people. Some of you have gone under the notion of Lord Prieſts, great Impropriators of Tythes and Donatives, and could licenſe authority, and give gifts to men, as ſpiritual <hi>Peters,</hi> that had the keys of Purgatory, but not the keys of heaven-gates: they could lock and unlock: they had all in their own hands, as if they had been ſpiritual Lords of heaven and earth. And truely what are ye Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and high Doctors? If the Biſhops were the cedars, you are the ſhrubs that muſt be pluckt up: for your power is like to burn, as one of the four Conſtellations: for your heavenly power ſhall go down with your earthly power, and ſhall be conſumed by inviſible fire from above. The univerſality of God ſhall ſo appear in fleſh, that men ſhall refuſe your teachings, and ſhall repair to the houſe of the Lord, ſaying, <hi>He will teach us of his ways:</hi> which will put an end to your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Miniſtery. When God teacheth, all ſhall be ſilenced; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſilenced, and people ſilenced, and every power ſilenced in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in earth. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>There was ſilence in heaven for the ſpace of half an hour:</hi> which declareth Gods wonderful works. When <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deum</hi> is in the midſt of his power, in the top of the mountains, your elevated powers ſhall cleave in ſunder, and every power ſhall ſhake and fall at the preſence of Chriſt the great King. Oh faithleſs generation, can ye not ſtand and live in faithfulneſs to Chriſt? he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth thee and me all things, how to live: he doth inherently teach every one that will ſavingly come to God; and <hi>none can come to the Father but by him:</hi> all other Teachers are but vain oſtentation, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118983:17"/> failable, but God inwardly teacheth. Ye high Doctors, petty Prieſts, Legators, and Merit-mongers, you that can teach the holy Ghoſt, ſaying ye have begotten ſouls, and have power to convert ſouls: truely in that ye are the greateſt deceivers in the world. Converſion is not from the letter of hiſtory; it is a work of great myſtery, beyond mens prating. Yet ſome of you will ſay, you have begotten many ſouls to Chriſt: which if ye can do ſo, ye may ſet up Meriting-houſes to pleaſe the people. It is not your much teaching that can do it: you be but Hiſtorians, all upon the literal hiſtory, not diſcerning the myſtery of Gods work, which is called Converſion: It is Gods work: let no dirt-danber meddle with converting of ſouls. But ſome of you Hiſtorian Prieſts will ſay, Did not <hi>Paul</hi> the great Doctor of the Gentiles convert ſouls? I anſwer, No. But did not <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> convert 3000 at one Sermon? Yes, he did ſo: but it was but to an outward conformity of Religion, as you train the people up to; and all is but in the outward, that ye can do: for ye are not the very Chriſt to do it. Then lay down: for renovation is a work of God, and not of man to do: and Miniſters ſtand for a cypher, and the men of <hi>Galilee</hi> ſtand gazing upon them. I am but a fool, yet not the ſon of folly: if I erre, I erre for Chriſt. He that giveth honour to m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, can never truely honour God. Silly people, have your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters perſwaded you all this while, ſaying they can convert ſouls, and cannot? O down with their power as lowe as Doctor <hi>Hills</hi> bones. Let their power be utterly diſſolved: for in Gods account they be no more then other men, and ſhall fall more contemptibly then the Biſhops: for they have hid the myſtery of iniquity, and kept it as a ſweet morſel under their tongues, and ſeduced the people. Theſe Merit-mongers, Legators, that keep the people under their bonds, meriting, Chriſts mediators betwixt God and the people, as if the hiſtory of the Bible could convert ſouls. Alas, no, it is not done by the hiſtory of mens works, neither can it be done by the example of Hiſtorian Fatherly Authors: it is not a work of hiſtory, but Gods work of myſtery to convert to ſalvation. Therefore, Prieſt, lay down thy power, and let the people ſpeak from the heavenly Univerſity, and as they be taught of God, ſo let them ſpeak from the All-ſpeaker, that ſhall teach both Miniſter and People. Ye Mediators, Miniſters, as ye call your ſelves, ye ſeduce many ſouls, and keep them under your yoke, from that freedom they have or might have in God; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free, and yet not free, by your bonds. O down with all ſuch yoke-Miniſters: <hi>if Chriſt hath made thee free, thou art free indeed:</hi> come no more under their yoke, but <hi>walk ſo, as thou mayſt be judged
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118983:17"/> by the law of liberty. John</hi> bids thee <hi>buy eye-ſalve,</hi> but not of men, which is an outward and vain oſtentation: it is not an outward know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that can do it: it is by a ſpiritual inward knowing that we live. You ſay that we <hi>receive faith by hearing,</hi> or <hi>the preaching of faith.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs outward faith may come by the letter preached; but ſaving faith is of the gift from above. Then ſalvation is onely of God, and not from the letter. Then how hard a thing is it for a Prieſt to convert ſouls? Even as to create the whole creation. Therefore, Doctor Prieſt, thou muſt ſurely lay down thy power: for thou haſt taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee a work of renovation, which is beyond Miniſters art and skill: for Chriſt is the ſouls ſolempnicy, and the firſt moving cauſe of our ſalvation: he is our Miniſter and ſollicitor, and ye diſſembling Chriſts that ſay ye have been means of mens ſalvation, and have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſouls to God; and call your ſelves ſoul-ſaving Miniſters. Ye falſe tongues, ſtop your mouthes for ſhame: ye Wiſe-men, Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, Prieſts and Legators, Definators, Merit-mongers, that call your ſelves the Seers in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or Watch-men over poor ſouls. Alas, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, your ſorrow is at hand. <hi>Mic.</hi> 3. ſaith, <hi>The ſeer ſhall be aſhamed, and the diviner confounded; they ſhall cover their mouth: for there is no anſwer of God.</hi> You call your ſelves ſoul-ſavers, but we may call you Wiſe-men that beguile the people, whoſe counſel ſhall ſtand but a while: for the Prophet <hi>Iſaih</hi> ſaith, <hi>Your counſellors ſhall be as at the firſt;</hi> taught of God, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> were. Chriſt and the Spirit of God is our great Counſellor, and ſhall be as Law and Teſtimony in us, that ſhall lead us in all truth: and thoſe be the two Witneſſes of the great Jehovah dwelling in us, which will confound every Miniſterial pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and every ordained power of man. For now is the time of the <hi>Elijah,</hi> and the Witneſſes prophecie. If ye be ſoul-ſaving Miniſters, then change the courſe of the rain if you can. You ſay you can and have converted ſouls; then you may as well change the courſe of drought, which is now a judgement upon the earth for three yeers and a half. But <hi>the Lord will make the heavens as braſs, and the clouds as iron.</hi> And under this three yeers and a half, the Witneſſes ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie in ſackcloth, though not utterly killed, as they have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law, and under the Law, and ſince Chriſt came in the fleſh, until now the opening of the ſixth Seal, which produceth life to the two Witneſſes, though by priſonment and ſackcloth, under this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Vial. Noble Pulpittian, thou muſt lay down four high titles, and give them up to Chriſt: Thy Miniſtery, Thy Prieſthood, Thy Power, and thy Teaching: for all this belongs to Chriſt. But thou ſayſt thou art an inſtrument. I doubt not but ye are ſome of thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118983:18"/> inſtruments ſpoken of by the Prophet <hi>Zechariah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>What are thoſe inſtruments in thy hand? he ſaid to me, Theſe were they that wounded me in the houſe of my friends.</hi> And the Lord ſaith he was wounded by ſuch inſtruments. You Miniſters may be outward Miniſters, and yet come ſhort of converting ſouls to God, but what ye can do outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a conformity, and no more. Thou art an inſtrument, but not inſtrumental; that is too high for man, ſeeing thou art but a creature: ſo I finde that there is no power in thy hand: thy inſtrument cannot do it; for he is inſtrumental, and not thou. Thou art haven, but he is havencial. Thou art a petty Prieſt, but he is an eternal Prieſt. Then become a fool, as I am, and throw down, that thou mayſt be made wiſe. For he is the Prieſthood-power; and glory renovation is of God, and not of men. Doctor, thou telleſt me thou art inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental; and ſo far thou ſpeakeſt an untruth: for it's proper onely to God. And thou art but ſtar, but he is ſtarreſtial. He is unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and thou art changeable. He is Miniſter, and thou but Star. Thou art an Angel, but he is Angelical. Thou art Man, but he is God. Chriſt is the Miniſter and Mediator of our ſouls; and therefore lay down thy care and charge of mens ſouls, and look to thy own ſoul, and ſay no more <hi>I am in Chriſts ſtead.</hi> Doctor, know that thine is an earthly authority, but Chriſt is a Miniſter by an heavenly authority. Then lay down thy falſe power. You ſay you are Miniſters of God, and yet can miniſter but the outward letter; and the letter ſhall non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſidence you, and ſuſpend your authority: for you are but falſe Chriſts. Therefore, Prieſt, thou muſt lay down: Chriſt is all thy Lectury: he is eggal, tyal, and ſubſtantial. You are but egg, but he is eggal. Therefore lay down, and ſay, We are no teachers, but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for righteouſneſs, mercy, and juſtice, and cannot teach the holy Ghoſt. Chriſt is the altar: then go no more to the Scribe, nor to any earthly teacher. If Chriſt be truely formed in thee, go no more to the Wiſe-man or the Scribe, which be inwardly ravening wolves; and yet they come in Chriſts name: which enjoy the tenth part of our Nation, called the Tythes and Impropriations, which might outwardly redeem the poor, the blinde, and the lame, the fatherleſs and widow. People, you look for an outward ſpeaking; but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpeaking is of God: It is the holy Ghoſt that ſpeaketh in thee, and me; and that is the ſureſt teaching, and ten thouſand times more good it will do thee, then all thy ſecond-hand-teachers, that cannot declare a true teſtimony. Then, all ye blinde guides that lead the blinde, the Lord doth rightly teach. Miniſters dare not expreſs themſelves, men dare not expreſs themſelves: therefore the truth of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118983:18"/> Chriſt muſt needs ſuffer violence. And I finde that theſe Wiſe-men and Counſellors are but the Witch of the world. Ye Pulpittians, there can be no election of Miniſters but by Chriſt, in whom he ſaid <hi>Go:</hi> it was in thoſe days a work of election onely of Chriſt, and from Chriſt, an Ordination tolerated by the Son of God: but now that power of election is of none effect: and let him be what he will, if a Miniſter or Lay-man, if he take upon him to ordain or elect any to be Miniſters of God, or to give any ſuch authority, he falſly ſtanderh in Chriſts place, and cometh not in at the door, but take Chriſts Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in their hand, and they are not called to it. The work of mans Prieſthood failed long ſince: for Chriſt is our high-prieſt once for all, and he ſtandeth <hi>a Prieſt for ever after the Order of Melchizedek.</hi> He ſhall purge the ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi> that they may bring an offering in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, which is to throw down their power at the eternal power, and live up to the endleſs Miniſtery of Chriſt; and ſhall ſay, I am no more a Miniſter of God, I am but as other men. Mens Prieſthoods have been ever held up with money, and outward territories: but Chriſt teacheth freely, and ſo did all they that he tolerated and ſent. All his diſciples were without reſting-places, ſo are not ye: he ſaid, <hi>The foxes have holes, and the birds of the air have neſts: but the Son of man hath nowhere to hide his head.</hi> Which of all the diſciples of Chriſt held up perſonal proprieties to themſelves? I am ſure amongſt them it was not a common thing, as it is amongſt you; for ſome of our Prieſts have large inheritances, and will rather loſe Chriſt, then loſe their Parſonages or great poſſeſſions of land. But Chriſt did not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain ſuch diſciples, but ſuch as were to carry neither ſcrip nor ſtaff to truſt to; ſhewing, that proprieties were not given them. <hi>Learn of me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: if I have nothing, what can you expect? if I be your example, be as I am. I tell thee, if thou beeſt never ſo high a Doctor, and eminent for gifts, and yet doſt buy and ſell the creation, thou art no Miniſter of God. Therefore lay down thy authority, for it is falſe. At the firſt, the Creation was not bought and ſold for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; it was to ſtand in its own original, and not to be traduced or ingroſſed by money, and ſo to be changed from its original. None of the Apoſtles bought or ſold the Creation for money, as ſome of our Doctors have done, which is utterly unlawful. Heaven is the Lords throne, and the earth his footſtool. Now, ye abominable Prieſts, that buy and ingroſs the earth into your hands, and tolerate all others ſo to do; can a man buy the Lords throne for money? No: for it his place of reſt: neither can ye buy the earth, which is his footſtool. Therefore ye Miniſters are buyers and ſellers, and as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-changers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118983:19"/> in the Temple of God: and for this cauſe of buying and ſelling the Creation, your Temple is broken in pieces, and there ſhall not be one ſtone leſt upon another, that ſhall not be thrown down. So that I clearly finde, that Ordination of Prieſts and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ceaſed at buying and ſelling the Creation: for then Chriſt came and put an end to their Miniſtery; and God appears chiefly to us by his Son, having him dwelling in us by the gift of the holy Ghoſt, that is the Law and Teſtimony in us: And God hath left power to his two Witneſſes to plead for righteouſneſs, becauſe there was no truth in the Prieſts: therefore he hath given the two Witneſſes power that ſhall hold to the end.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <p>DOctor, I ſee nothing but an end of all Traditional preaching: for Mediumal preacheth in the mount of his power, and requireth ſetting up thrones, and to bring all things before the ſeat of juſtice. Chriſt muſt ſit upon his ſeat, and judge the ends of the earth. He is ſaid to ſit upon twelve thrones, that is, by an audiencee of twelve voices, to vindicate and make out the full truth by Witneſſes. Then where is your preaching power? your grinding in a Mill will ceaſe. Ye ſtand beating the Pulpit, but all is in vain: for the honourable ſeat of Juſtice will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all your ſeenal Witcheraſts. You have preached long, yet no juſtice, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, nor truth is in our borders. But the Prophet <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>chariah</hi> ſaith, <hi>In thoſe days, and at that time, many ſhall be joyned to the Lord:</hi> which ſheweth they ſhall throw off the Miniſteries of men. And the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith, <hi>They ſhall be ſowed to the Lord in truth, in merc<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, and loving kindneſs, ſaith the Lord: I will betroth thee unto me.</hi> That ſhews that every one ſhould underſtand and know their Mariage union with Chriſt, and come out from Prieſt and People. It is not enough to ſay thou art a Chriſtian, but thou muſt prove thy ſelf by an inward Law and teſtimony, with the approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the grand Church, that is, by an inward and outward teſtimony, that ſhall make them free. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. <hi>There remaineth a reſt to the people of God:</hi> and in verſ. 10. <hi>He that is entred into that reſt, hath ceaſed from his own works, as God did from his.</hi> This Chriſtian reſt is perfection of parts, without toyl and legal cate, having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſanctity in the ſoul, which is a ſweet Sabbath-reſt; and I know no other Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. You obſerve days called Sundays outwardly, and do not look to the inward Sabbath, to reſt in <hi>God.</hi> I wonder who hath bewitched you from the eternal reſt, Doctors and Miniſters. Once in that ſetled reſt made free in Chriſt, then free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. The houſhold of faith are no more under your Legalities: once free in Chriſt, free indeed: he is our true vine, and miniſtreth to us the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> and ſetteth us at liberty from all the earthly Chriſts, to live by the ſpirit of life; and Chriſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in us, that maketh us inwardly and outwardly free from the traditional and literal teachings of men. Once in covenant with Chriſt, and for ever ſallowmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the fellowſhip of the <hi>Son of God,</hi> by a ſolempniſie or ſetled union with the Lord, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> did free from the teachings of men that came in his name, and are not the very Chriſt, but deceive the people, uſing many words, yet Chriſt never did ſo; he ſpake few words, and the people anſwered him. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Apoſtles did ſo, by diſciplying and anſwering Diſputations. Every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to be in a married union with Chriſt, and ſo throw off the Prieſts, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118983:19"/> cry, <hi>Abraham, Abraham our father, after the order of Melchizedek, a Prieſt for ever.</hi> Chriſt a Prophet, a Prieſt, a Teacher, a Fore-runner, and ſo throw off all Legators that ſtand as Lawyers in their Pulpits, pleading Mediators betwixt <hi>God</hi> and many mens ſouls. But <hi>Melchizedek</hi> was a Prieſt long before <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt, or any high Prieſt of you all. Chriſt was and is a Prieſt unchangeable, but you are inſtruments in his hand. I do not call you Miniſters: becauſe you deſtroy the Offering of <hi>Gods</hi> Temple, ſo you ſhall be deſtroyed, and your change it is nigh at hand. <hi>God</hi> had an houſe before any Prieſt of <hi>Levi</hi> was, whereof <hi>Gods</hi> extent was firſt extended by an Ordinance ordained to <hi>Abraham,</hi> which was the Tenth of all his ſubſtance, that ſhould go to the houſe of <hi>God;</hi> whereof <hi>Abraham</hi> brought in the Tenth of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance unto the houſe of <hi>God,</hi> after the order of <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> after <hi>Gods</hi> order. And becauſe you have denied theſe things, therefore your Prieſtdom ſhall ceaſe, and your power ſhall go down. You <hi>S<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>onets,</hi> Miniſters of <hi>God,</hi> as you call your ſelves, though but outward inſtruments, ſuch as have wounded the Lord in the houſe of his friends. The Prophet <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>chariah</hi> much complaineth againſt all ſuch miniſtring inſtruments, as Pulpittians, men of conformity, as if their conformity was the way to ſalvation. Thoſe are inſtruments indeed that teach ſalvation, and yet not the very Chriſt, yet come in his Name, and deceive many, and will not loſe one days teaching of the people by no means, but will get one <hi>Sionet</hi> or another to learn the people ſalvation, and will give the man that ſtands in their abſence twenty ſhillings for his Sabbath-days work of preaching conformity to the people night and morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as if the way of conformity was the very way to ſalvation: and thus one Prieſt gratifieth another for money, as if ſalvation could be bought with money. O out with all money-changers of the Temple: for the Lord will cut off the name of <hi>Baal</hi> out of the earth, that ſtand bawling with their own tongues for money. And are not theſe money-changers of the ſeenal Witchcrafts very ſubtil and crafty, yet call themſelves the Miniſters of <hi>God?</hi> ſimple inſtruments in his hand. We may call a ſpade a ſpade in ones hand: for what is one man more then another? When <hi>God</hi> is inſtrumental, and teacheth us all, by his <hi>Son,</hi> a Prieſt for ever: he is inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, and not man. Fooliſh man may take upon him Chriſts office, and ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf high as Scribe over the people, yet he ſhall come down to plead among his low equals. Wo to you Scribes, Phariſees, and Hypocrites, ye outſide Preachers of the letter, and cannot miniſter the ſpirit; for <hi>God</hi> inwardly teacheth, and ſo will do, when all your forms are down: for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall all be taught of God, from the leaſt to the greateſt;</hi> which is a far higher teaching then that of men. The next thing that I ſhall treat upon, is my deſire to ſee the people come out from thoſe falſe Chriſts, and be married to Chriſt Jeſus in the new Covenant, which is a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſpiritual marriage, made free in him, and come no more under Legators yoke. To be taught of <hi>God,</hi> is to live by the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> without the teachings of men: and that is to <hi>ſtand in the liberty wherewith Christ hath made us free,</hi> and come no more under their yoke of bondage, but live up to Ordination, which is above the teachings of men. Though they call themſelves Miniſters of <hi>God,</hi> believe them not: for our Lord ſaith they be falſe Chriſts that come in his name. And truely thoſe be the men that call themſelves Converters, and ſoul-ſavers of the people, or the feet that bring glad tidings of ſalvation, and ſo nuzzle up the poor ignorant people. O come out from thoſe falſe Chriſts, and ſee your freedom and liberty in Jeſus Chriſt: come out, and ſtand upon your feet, as faithful, Witneſſes raiſed of the dry bones, redeemed from the ſpawn of <hi>Euphrates;</hi> I mean, from the Prieſts, that preach up their own ſelf-honour, and cunningly keep to themſelves the heritage of <hi>Gods</hi> houſe by a carnal and uſurped authority, that call themſelves inſtrumental, when indeed they are but formed inſtruments in his hand, and as low as others, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118983:20"/> have wounded him in the houſe of his friends. The Lord is miniſterial and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, without the help of men, or any ſuch Merit-mongers that have ſtood ſo long in their Pulpits as Mediators betwixt <hi>God</hi> and ſo many thouſand poor ſouls. Theſe ſatisfactorious Prieſts, not ordained of <hi>God,</hi> nor ſent of Chriſt, yet they run, and call themſelvs Curates of mens ſouls, and Miniſters of <hi>God,</hi> as if the work of <hi>God</hi> were in their hands. Miſerable blind guides that deceive the people; feigned Chriſts; Ambaſſadors, as they call themſelves, as if Chriſt were not in all places to preach ſalvation without them. Doctor, what will you do when your Churches ſtand forlorn, and your people withdraw themſelvs; when the Lord will be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in every place? then what will become of your <hi>Jeruſalems,</hi> when <hi>God</hi> will be known in every place, and the people not tyed to your formed Churches? Your forms muſt ceaſe and go down. I cannot ſee but <hi>Gods</hi> people that have enjoyed the cleareſt light from above, have ever bin perſecuted by your Miniſters and Clergical power; if not by Biſhops, yet by ſecret counſellors that call themſelves Miniſters of <hi>God.</hi> Though they may ſet themſelves high, and ſeem to take away ſome of the power of Chriſt, yet <hi>God</hi> will blaſt their ſeenal Witchcrafts and cunning ſophiſtry. Though they may call themſelves by thoſe great names, yet the Witch ſhall be cut out of the earth. I cannot tell, but I am ſure ye have made your ſelvs rich and great, juſtitious and high, by robbing <hi>Gods</hi> houſe of Tythes and common rights, and yet can ſet nothing in order, but preach on in the old road: but what is that to the ſetting up of thrones, that all clear juſtice may proceed? I can behold nothing but diſcovery, diſcovery. The <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith, <hi>The moon and ſtars ſhall be as the ſun;</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſeeming brightneſs in them all, or ſome equality with the ſun: which petypeth and prefigureth a great diſcovery of Chriſt and his <hi>Saints,</hi> by ſome new diſciplying way Eccleſiaſtical and Civil. We muſt come to a higher beholding of <hi>God,</hi> which ſhall be marvelous in the eyes of the remnant, when they ſhall throw off your old cuſtoms and forms: your <hi>Sacraments</hi> will be changeable. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That ye do, do in remembrance of me till I come.</hi> And truly that is when he cometh by a new light: then all your old forms ſhall be taken away; and to that purpoſe, he ſpeaks of a <hi>new Covenant that he will make with the people, not according to the old:</hi> he ſaith, <hi>All things ſhall become new.</hi> That declareth that old forms muſt be taken away by a more excellent power that ſhall ſtand for the ordering of ſpiritual affairs and civil affairs, brought all into one, called <hi>The law of Sion,</hi> that ſhall be governed by twelve or by four and twenty, according to Ordination; and ſo to cut off all forms that have been erected by Biſhops and Prieſts. The Lord hath raiſed me by the degrees of light, and ſtill one light hath fruſtrated another, ſo that the Lord hath followed me with new lights, &amp; cauſed me to throw off the old: for the <hi>Sacrament</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is declared to me as an outward thing, and cannot ſtand when the Lord cometh in power by a new light. He ſaith to his diſciples, <hi>Do as I have commanded you, and lo I will be with you to the end.</hi> It implieth, that he will be with his people in the Old and new work: but the new light ſhall do away the old. Doctor Presbytian, thou cryeſt, <hi>Down with water-baptiſm:</hi> then why doſt thou baptize babes in clouts? <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Neither circumciſion nor Baptiſm availeth, but a new creature.</hi> Chriſt went into the water: and I think that to be more tolerable, then to baptize babes that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand or ſpeak. This difference of Baptiſm will not be ended, until we lay down both the forms of outward diſcipline. And if ye deny it to them of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, then for ſhame leave off diſcipling of babes that have no underſtanding, and let every one chiefly ſee himſelf to be a new creature, baptized in Chriſt Jeſus by a new Covenant, for throwing off old forms and authors of men, that be ſo failable and ſuperfluous: ſo that I find every form muſt come to the formal power of Chriſt; for he is that all power to ſettle our differences, and to make known the living <hi>Goſpel</hi>
                           <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118983:20"/> to every creature: it is far higher then the letter: it is the power of Chriſt that is our true teſtimony by an inward law of conſcience, called <hi>The two Teſtimonies,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The two Witneſſes,</hi> without which none can ſavingly prove themſelves Chriſtians: ſo that every one ought not to live by the teaching of others, but effectually to ſee ſomething of <hi>God</hi> in themſelves, otherwiſe outward teaching will but intoxicate the brain, and cannot reſtollize thy ſoul. Then look not ſo much upon outward forms, which have no ſubſtance in them. It is not your <hi>Sacraments</hi> or <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> or Baptiſms or Preachings: it is onely ſomething of <hi>God</hi> within us, that moveth us to work righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs: Outward oſtentations or cuſtoms cannot do it; for they are failable. When Chriſt comes to us by true faith, thoſe forms muſt be done away by an higher light, called his bright appearing, that ſhall aboliſh all the Antichriſtian forms, when men ſhall know <hi>God</hi> in ſpirit and in truth, without old Popery. The Papiſts look upon Chriſt by their Crucifix, and you look upon Chriſt by your Forms, ſo that all of you look upon the ſepulchre, or upon ſomething below Chriſt, giving your ſelves content and reſt in outward ſhadows.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="testimony">
                        <p>THe honourable ſeat of Juſtice, or two Olive-trees, the two branches ſtanding on both ſides the bank of the river, called the conduit-pipes, that receive the Oyl, and declare it forth, the ſweet Odours, theſe two Olive-trees are called the bowls on both ſides of the Altar, or the two Candleſticks, or two Anoynted ones ſtanding before the great <hi>God</hi> of the earth; which indeed are the two Witneſſes that ſhal faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully plead for all truth at the right hand, three on the one hand, and three on the other: thoſe ſix ſhall attend one witneſs; the other witneſs ſhall be attended with other ſix in the ſame order, twelve on one ſide, and twelve on the other, four and twenty in number, with two Witneſſes ſtanding on both ſides, which may be called the ſeat of Juſtice, for Chriſt to ſit and rule upon his throne: he is the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> in the midſt of them, ſaid to be the Altar of gold, that ſhall ſit upon the throne of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, called <hi>Davids</hi> throne, ſitting upon twelve thrones, which is the ends of the earth, or remnant of the tribes. Thoſe two faithful Witneſſes that ſhall ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſeat of Juſtice, ſhall plead for equity in all conſiderable places and nations; and all ſuch thrones ſhall be called the ſeat of Juſtice: they ſhall put forth Queries and anſwer: as the one declareth, the other ſhall anſwer in due order: ſo that twelve <hi>Senators</hi> ſhall judge and declare their ſentence, to prove every truth, which ſhall be excellent, ſweet, and amiable, ſo that people ſhall abominate their earthly Chriſts that have deluded them ſo long, and look upwards to the miniſter of <hi>God,</hi> the higheſt teacher. Our Prieſts are not like the Prophets of old, that quaked and trembled when they ſaw danger at hand: there hath been a great deal of difference between the Prieſts and the Prophets. The Prieſts have ever been proud, and high, and much ſought themſelves by ſelf-greatneſs; which doth not prove themſelves Miniſters of <hi>God,</hi> but ſtand in a Miniſters place, as if they were the very Chriſt; which go in ſheeps clothing, yet ravenous and cruel as the Biſhops, if they had the ſame power. But for all their Presbytian ſting, the pricking brier muſt be taken away, that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Chriſt is the fountain and finiſher of the work: he ſets his foot on mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> and it cleaveth in ſunder: ſo ſhall your Miniſterial power be daſhed in ſunder; and happie ſhall he be called that daſheth your power in pieces, for the raiſing up the dry bone of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Chriſt ſent his diſciples or by two and two: he called fiſhermen, not one man. One Prieſt ought not to ſtand ſo high, to elevate his own tongue: he will not have one ſpeaker; but by the mouth of two or three faithful witneſſes truth ſhall be proved, from one end of the earth to another, though <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118983:21"/> our blind guides ſee it not. Therefore their tongues ſhall be no more an Allegator; it muſt be two, called the two Olive-trees, that ſhall ſtand before the great <hi>God</hi> of the earth to prove the truth. Two candleſticks and two lights before the people, when one mans tongue ſpeaking ſhall be a lye: every ſingular power ſhall be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, onely Chriſt ſhall ſtand ſingular over all. He ſet his foot upon the hinder ſea, and his other foot upon the far ſea: he cleaveth the mount of <hi>Olivet</hi> in ſunder, and will diſelevate all your hiſtorical power, which ſhall be the beginning of the downfal of your Prieſtly power: for Chriſt will ſit upon it by twelve thrones, &amp; will diſ-throne all that ſtand ſo high in the place of oſtentation, they muſt come down and plead for truth among their lowe equals: for their mount is cleft in ſunder, from the hinder ſea to the far ſea. There ſhall no power ſtand before Chriſt, the <hi>new Jeruſalem;</hi> for none ſhall ſtand ſingular in place of ſpeaking, but Chriſt alone, and his two anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ones. Therefore Alphaba, it muſt down with thy all power of preaching in thine own tongue. Now Chriſt doth appear, your mount <hi>Elevate</hi> is cleft in ſunder: there ſhall not be one ſtone left upon another, that ſhall not be thrown down. And happy ſhall be that man that ſhall take your power and daſh it againſt the wall. <hi>Zech.</hi> 11. 10. <hi>I took my ſtaff Beauty and brake it in ſunder, and it was broke in that day: ſo the ſheep that waited upon me knew that I was the word of the Lord.</hi> And truely he that brake the ſtaff Beauty, wil ſurely break the ſtaff Bands, that your elevated power may fall. Chriſt is the Middinal <hi>Sainter</hi> or Mediator betwixt two: he ſtandeth as a tree of Muſtard-ſeed, little in ſhew, yet great and orient in ſubſtance, and ſplendorious to all: and his name is <hi>Branch,</hi> that is, beautiful, and ſhall grow up in the earth. He is the tree of life ſtanding in the garden of <hi>God;</hi> and whoever eateth of it, ſhall live for ever. He is life eternal to all that thirſt after him. He is a Medium of comfort to all the oppreſſed: he will in ſome meaſure ſtill the rage of the ſea. Chriſt the Lord he is all righteouſneſs. You may definate, but Chriſt is the definer of truth. He is the Centre, and ſtable medium of all things in heaven and in earth. He is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that filleth the two conduit-pipes with oyl, called <hi>The two anoynted ones,</hi> that ſtand before the <hi>God</hi> of the whole earth. He filleth every Lamp with oyl. Every high hill ſhall cleave aſunder at his preſence. <hi>Who art thou, O mountain? before Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbabel thou ſhalt become a plain.</hi> For every power ſhall be cleft in ſunder before Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>middium the Lord: he ſhall ſtand upon the ſea with his face toward the hinder ſea: he and his two Witneſſes ſhall ſtand in power, to deſtroy the Red Dragon and his fury. The faithful Witneſſes of <hi>God</hi> ſhall ſtand by many two's, yet one ſhall ſtand in the midſt of them, which is the tree of life Angelical. <hi>And if any ſhall attempt or hurt them, fire cometh down from heaven, and ſhall deſtroy them.</hi> This Angelical power of Chriſt with his <hi>Saints</hi> Evangelical, ſhall ſtrike the hinder parts of Leviathan, which is the Dragons tayl; ſo that fire from heaven ſhall burn up his fury: for the jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of the Lord is gone forth, and ſhall not return, till it hath wrought the full work of <hi>God: for lo, ſaith the Lord, the ſtone that I have laid before Joſhua, upon it ſhall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven eyes;</hi> which ſheweth the glory of Chriſt, that taketh away the iniquity of the land in one day; and that ſhall be when we make the Lord our Miniſter: then he ſhall take away our reproach. Chriſt the heavenly Branch ſhall ſilence all fleſh. Men may preach all their days, and cannot remove our reproach; yet Chriſt can make our <hi>Goſpel</hi> peace. Mans preaching is but carnal policie. But Chriſt is raiſed out of his place; let men and Miniſters be ſilent: he hath the key of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pit; he took the dragon &amp; bound him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. <hi>he ſet a ſeal upon him, that he ſhould deceive the nations no more, tell certain yeers expired.</hi> The time when he was firſt bound, was about 1600 yeers ago, or thereabout. And <hi>God</hi> hath ſhewed himſelf the more merciful, in keeping us from his perſonal viſage; for ſo long ſince <hi>God</hi> hath ſhut him up under chains of darkneſs; and from thence to this day his common appearance hath been hideous to man.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118983:21"/>
            <p>YE Aſſyrian Prieſts, it is not your way to ſave ſouls, it is proper to God alone; ye may counſel them, or inform them, that's all ye can do: for God alone teacheth, <hi>I will write my Law in their inward parts.</hi> He ſpiritually teacheth and infuſeth grace in the ſoul. Prieſts and Levites, it was to you for a time, but our Miniſters for a ſhorter time: if mens Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood failed under the Law, how much more ſhall yours be under Chriſt? and as the Prieſts were cryed down under the Law by the Prophets, how much more failable are you, under the eternal Prieſthood of Chriſt? for all Tythes, and Levitical forms of Tythes have ceaſed ſince Chriſt came in the fleſh. If <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt could have no inheritance amongſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what benefits can ye expect under the everlaſting Goſpel? Tythes were given at the firſt by a legal power of men, and therefore it was called Legal, or Levitical, pretending td Gods houſe, or to the righteouſneſs of God, till Chriſt came in the fleſh, which cut off old Levitical forms by a new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, nor according to the old, ſaying, <hi>I will make a new Covenant with them, and write my Law in their inward parts:</hi> as an eternal Sabbath in the conſcience, that ſhall burn up every outward form. When Chriſt appeared in the fleſh, all Tythes and forms of ſlavery ſure ceaſed. Truly Doctor thou maiſt ſay what thou wilt, yet I cannot believe thee; though thou ſaiſt, Thou art Chriſts Diſciple; yet I ſay thou art not, except thou denieſt thy ſelf by a ceſſation of Tythe-forms, for they muſt all ceaſe, there cannot a bit of Levitical Prieſthood ſtand before Chriſt Jeſus the eternal Prieſt: every Prieſthood muſt down, for that made the Law a Law, and the Divel a Divel: Chriſt Jeſus is a free Paſtor to all that come unto him: and all ye Doctors and Miniſters are a generation of Angels muſt fall, calling your ſelves Miniſters of Chriſt for the Tythe, and for the Fleece for money and Glebe-land; ye ſit as little Biſhops gaping under a ſunny bank, ſo fat and ſo proud, and no Diſciples of Chriſt in his poverty. Therefore Biſhop-black ſhall array himſelf in Sheeps-clothing among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that be his low equals: Chriſt is the royal Shepherd in the Mount. Al-medium preacheth in the Mount, and your Miniſterial power ſhall go down: he ſet his foot upon Mount Olivet, and it cleft in ſunder; ſo ſhall your elevated power divide in ſunder.</p>
            <p>Now Al-medium preacheth in the Mount, your Miniſterial preaching ſhall go down, your Olivet will cleave in ſunder: you go to your mercenary mediating houſes; but Chriſt is all in all to me, he is a Mediator, and a Miniſter without your deffinating. It is not your Church going, or all your preaching that can do me any good; but what I have received inwardly of God, that keepers my life. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that heareth me, heareth him that ſent me; and he that believeth me, believeth him that ſent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118983:22"/> me;</hi> ſo that we ought to believe Chriſt, and be taught of him alone, for teachings of men are not the ſpirit of truth. He ſaith, <hi>If I go away, I will ſend you the Comforter, that ſhall teach you in all truth:</hi> ſo that we muſt prove every ſpirit, and hear the voice of Chriſt onely: once in the Lord, and ever in him; once a year, and ever from year to year to keep a Sabbath on Earth as it is in Heaven: and ſo ſtand free and effectual, to ſtand and live, and live and ſtand faſt in the liberty wherein Chriſt hath made us free, and be no more entangled under the yoke of bondage of Prieſts, that are in ſo many mindes, and know not the truth. Twenty Miniſters, twenty mindes, and yet Mediators of the letter, and tie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to obſerve dayes and new-moons, beggerly rudiments, full of lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and ſuperfluity of words. I wonder the world is ſo miſerably ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by them, as if they could teach Heaven in the Maſs-houſes or Churches, as ye call them, which if men could teach Heaven, what need we then to look upon Chriſt, having ſo many merit-mongers, or ſoul-ſaving Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters? Oh but ſay they, We declare the minde of God and Chriſt to the people, as if God were not preſent in all places, or as if he were afar off and muſt have Embaſſadours to ſatisfie his elect. Oh ye blinde guides, doth not God keep up the full creation by a providence? then much more by his power; for Almedium teacheth in the Mount of his power, which is far above your teachings: and truly it is for you to leave off teaching, that have ſtood ſingularly in Chriſts place ſo long, and done little good: it is time now to call an aſſembly to ſit, and ſet up thrones for Juſtice. Oh people, ye men of <hi>Galilee</hi> that ſtand gazing, I believe I ſhall ſee you ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor your earthly gods, and look upwards: I mean, you ſhall abominate all thoſe leaders of ſilly women, that bewitch the world in their own forms. Can we think God is tied to the outward means once a week? Is not he the ſame every day, yeſterday, to day, and for ever? Ye end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workers, that object and ſay, Ye be the means that God hath ordained: ye falſe Chriſts, Mediators, that ſtand ſo high to limit that holy one of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> Is not God and his Son wiſe enough, but they muſt have your help? Had not we <hi>Abraham, Moſes,</hi> and the Prophets, and the Son of God after them, to confirm all that are once entered into the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Sons of God, which is a free ſtate, free from the teaching power of a man, and being ſet at liberty by Jeſus Chriſt? Then let us be no more entangled under their Prieſtly yoke. Ye ſilly ſimple Prieſts, you muſt come under the teachings of God, as all other men muſt do: when Juſtice, Divine Thrones of Juſtice are ſet up, then God will purge all you ſons of Levi.</p>
            <p>But methinks I hear ſome high Prieſts ſay, <hi>Why do you not quote Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to prove what you write?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118983:22"/>
            <p>My anſwer is, Chriſt is the end of legal Scriptures, and you have quoted Scriptures long enough, and could never make out truth: Chriſt is the word, and the end of all Scriptures, and ſtandeth in his place, when all Scriptures ſhall be failable, and every viſion ſhall be unfolded at the beatifical viſion of Chriſt Jeſus: and truly Scriptures are good, but Chriſt is the principal; then let us hold faſt to the principal, and wave the letter, Chriſt is the foundation, and every mans work ought to be built upon him. Men and Prophets in the old time ſpake as they were moved by inſpiration, and yet it was but by the by, or by the moving power of the holy Ghoſt; ſo being written by the inſpiration of Chriſt, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he is the Word far beyond all Scripture written by men that ſtand but by Chriſt, and are failable when he cometh in power. He is the chief medium and principal Senator, and we muſt throw off our earthly gods, I mean, all our Prieſts, onely to reſt upon him; for until then we ſhall have no true Sabbath. He is our Sabbath: if we come out from the Prieſts, then he will give us true reſt: he is our Vine to live under: therefore my bowels yearne over the people to ſee them led off from Chriſt, by legating Prieſts, as wiſe-men and Lawyers, ſtanding in Pulpits, when grave Chriſtians ſhall be taught by ſome young boyes ſtanding in their Prieſtly Office, ſo high in Pulpits: it is a great ſhame that godly men and women do not come out from them, and ſtand upon their feet, and ſay, Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is my Teacher, I have been much deluded by proud Prieſts, by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Prieſts, by ſcandalous Prieſts, by young Prieſts, by ruffinly Prieſts, by ſwearing Prieſts, by literal Prieſts, by hiſtorical Prieſts, and by deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſts, that have kept us from the power of Chriſt, and freedom of Sabbath, tying the people to their ſet-forms, or what they call a Sabbath. Their maſs and dirge ſhall down, for every form ſhall ceaſe but one, and that is the Government of Chriſt that ſhall ſtand, when all your Prieſtly power ſhall lie as low as Doctor <hi>Hill's</hi> bones. Doctor, thou canſt prove but one calling, and that was a Law to <hi>Adam,</hi> That thou ſhouldſt work and labour by the ſweat of thy brows, as others do, none excepted, and no other calling of Miniſtery canſt thou prove. Therefore thou muſt without diſpute throw down thy trade of preaching at Chriſts feet of two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes called the Law and Teſtimony writ in thy conſcience.</p>
            <p>People, I can but controverſe with you: ye ſay ye know God, and love God, and fear God. I ſay, No, ye know the Prieſts ye fear the Prieſts, and ye love the Prieſts, otherwayes ye would renounce their wayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chriſts. The Prieſts are diſſemblers, but Chriſt is our true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. They tell thee a fair tale, that Chriſt is ſimply good, he is full of pure ſimplicity, an high attribute, ſo low, yet above all the Prieſts: how are ye married to Chriſt, and yet follow after fained lovers? If Chriſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118983:23"/> hath redeemed you, think it enough: follow not after thoſe that deceive ſilly men and women, and lead them captive from Chriſt, as if we could not enjoy Chriſt without the teachings of men: having the Spirit of God and the Scripture, with the example of Chriſt and the Prophets, and having ſo much Apoſtolical divine light, methinks they might guide us in the true way. Methinks I ſee the Prieſts grow ſhamed the light diſcovereth their veile caſt over the people, and the people begin to ſee them ſo black, and Chriſt in his brightneſs ſo pure, in a heavenly ſhape: but the Prieſts are as Locuſts that ſhall fall under Armegiddon: Euphrates ſhall dry up. Oh Army, Army, Arme of the Lord, their power ſhall fall under thee.</p>
            <p>Prieſt, thou ſayeſt thy power is a ſpiritual power, yet it is but a civil power; and therefore it muſt down and fall before <hi>Sion.</hi> The overthrow of the Biſhops was for calling it a ſpiritual, and for their ſpiritual courts audacious to think upon, full of blaſphemies, ſet up by an Antichriſtial power, which now is thrown down as contemptible: therefore all your civil Chriſts muſt down, as your Spiritual Fathers the Biſhops have done; if you call your power Eccleſiaſtial, it is equal with Chriſts; if you call it Eccleſiaſtical, you muſt prove it from Chriſts ſaying <hi>Go teach,</hi> whoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination ceaſed after the Apoſtles; ſo that your Authority of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> is void and cannot ſtand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4 and 5. <hi>He hath choſen us in himſelf, before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world was laid: he predeſtinated us to the adoption of children by Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> but not by your Miniſtery. You ſee the Saints, were firſt choſen, predeſtinated and called before, your Miniſtery ſtood up: and yet you ſay you are called to convert ſouls in the Pulpit. You Prieſts muſt have a hand in the work of renovation, though you are not called yet ye run, and are not ſent to do ſuch works of wonder; for it is he alone that doth abound to us in love, in wiſdom, and in prudency, <hi>Having made known to us the myſtery of his will,</hi> verſ. 6. <hi>according to his good pleaſure, which he had purpoſed in himſelf,</hi> and not by your means, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.4. and 5. <hi>God who is rich in all mercy hath quickned us,</hi> which ſheweth that it is not your teaching that can do it: and elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>By his grace you are ſaved, and not of works.</hi> Then down with theſe working teaching Chriſts, that can learn the people ſalvation: for <hi>it is the gift of God: not of works left any man ſhould boaſt,</hi> Epheſ. 2.9. and 10. <hi>For we are his workmanſhip created to good works, which God hath foreordained:</hi> therefore it is properly and fully the work of God freely to our ſouls: but let no durt-dawbing Prieſt have any hand in thy converſion; for it is Gods work. Let no ſwine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd meddle with ſuch a pearl, as if they were outward means of mens ſalvation. He alone is our peace, who hath broke down the mid-wall of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118983:23"/> our reproach having aboliſhed the enmity, even the Law of Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments contained in Ordinances, by making in himſelf of twain, one new man for peace, that he might reconcile both into one body by his <hi>croſs, having ſlain the enmity thereby,</hi> Epheſ. 2.17. <hi>He preached peace to you afar off, and to them that are nigh:</hi> ſo that by him we have acceſs to the Father, and not by the Prieſts of the ſecond hand, which have little skill in the creation of ſalvation, it is a ſecret work of God. Let no man ſay he can teach: but let us all be taught of God, Miniſter and People, from the leaſt to the greateſt: let us all covenant to him with one conſent, and betroth our ſelves to him, that he may take pleaſure in his Spouſe, and his beloved ones may have pleaſure in him the All-teacher, and come out from their fained Prieſts the gods of their Temples, that call themſelves Miniſters of God, ſaying, <hi>The people muſt reverence them as Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, for the works ſake:</hi> as if God had not power on earth aſwell as in heaven: he is preſent in all places by his omnipotency and omnipreſence, and by his immenſity, and by his all-ſeeing eye, and by his providence that governeth the whole creation, and by his inſpiration and foreknowing what ſhall come to paſs, he ſpiritually beholdeth all things, he alone hath created the earth; then doth he not ſee and teach all, and will bring all rule and power under himſelf? Then lay down, ye high Prieſts, and ſay, Ye are all taught of God; for he will teach us of his wayes, <hi>The Law ſhall go out of Sion, and the word of the Lord from Jeruſalem,</hi> which ſhall be Chriſt preaching from the Mount, when the people ſhall give au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to him, and caſt off their fained Prieſts, which are but as wood and ſtraw, whoſe ſtubble ſhall burn before the fire of his jealouſie; wangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall their power be, when God ſhall give power to his two Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the Law ſhall preach out of <hi>Sion, Revel.</hi> 14. The everlaſting Goſpel ſhall preach to every language and nation, when all your wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Prieſts ſhall be forced to lay down, becauſe they can eſtabliſh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in order correſpondent to his bright appearing: therefore they muſt lay down and ſay, We have ſpent our time in vain too long, and beſotted the ſimple people; and yet we have ſaid, We were the ordained Miniſters of God, though we were deſtroyers and no builders: hiſtorians that have preached this or that; but what of the new work can we do? it is not our talking of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> that will ſerve the turn: for God will make a new heaven and a new earth, by a new diſcipline Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, he will make all new, to do away your carnal formes, every form ſhall ceaſe to a new formality, God will make his latter temple more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then all the former. All earthly builders ſhall not be found fit for the work of Gods houſe, every flatterer ſhall be nonreſidenſed, and caſt out according to Gods extent, and laid open to the ſight of the grand Church,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118983:24"/> to be excluded from the common community, ſhut out of fellowſhip and ſociety with the unſociable and rebukeable. When God ſhall try <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſearch <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with lights, when he ſhall purge the Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> and break the conſtellations that ſtand ſo high, and remove the ſtars out of their places, when the moon ſhall bluſh and be aſhamed, and all the ſtars come under his feet, when this diſcipline that now ſtandeth upon crutches ſhall be taken away, then you may declare the great things of God, ſaying, He hath formed a new temple, wherein all righteouſneſs ſhall dwell. Old things are become new, and all faſhions and forms are paſſed away, but onely one, which is called the formal Power and Government of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> and God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is our Temple. The Lord is our light within us, he is our Sabbath: the Sun ſhall not burn us by day, neither ſhall the dark Night overſhade thee: thou ſhalt conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually walk in the light of the Citie of the great King; when thou ſhalt throw off thy fained lovers, I mean thy Prieſts that erre in darkneſs, and know not the true way; for God will ſurely conſume the ſmoak of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and burn up all darkneſs before himſelf, that he may diſſolve the great blindeneſs and ignorance of the Prieſts, that there may be light in the City, that hath lain ſo long under darkneſs, ſuſpended from the truth, lying under thick darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Therefore we muſt all come under the teachings of God, which will be a ſtable peaceable Government; when we ſhall ſtrive no more for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplying Miniſters. Your power that you hold up, is full of many horns of the beaſts puſhing and perſecuting in your thought, ſuch as will not come under your bow: but God will have a peaceable dominion, when your power lies as low as Doctor <hi>Hill's</hi> bones.</p>
            <p>This is a hard doctrine to you, which you have not learned at <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> yet you muſt ſtoop to his dominion. Chriſtians and People, how have you been deluded in your way, and ſolely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited in earthly Prieſts? Is not Chriſt all in all? Ye look upon mortal man to teach, yet God hath a providence that teacheth and ruleth all things in heaven and in earth. Doth he not guide Winter and Summer? and every ſeaſon declareth his wiſdom: and by his power dark things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare forth the light; that the people may know, there is an higher Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery then that of men.</p>
            <p>Doctor Pulpitian know this the more you tie men to your audience, the more they ſhall break off from your tyecal ties, and your hearers ſhall be few in number.</p>
            <p>Further know this, When they turn their backs upon you, there will be a great conſumption of your power, as we may call a conſumption of the lungs, or an endleſs conſuming, ſo that you ſhall be a hopeleſs Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118983:24"/> for Chriſt is the beginning and end of every work, and all truth is from the Father and the Son. Chriſt never reſiſted the powers, but ſaid, <hi>Give tribute to whom tribute belongeth:</hi> he further ſaid, <hi>Give Caeſar his due.</hi> He was circumciſed, he read the Law, he went into the water and was baptized; yet all things are failable when he cometh in power: then all ſuch cuſtomes and forms muſt be done away, though he ſuffered all after the fleſh; yet he redeemed all by a ſpiritual power, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſe for every wrong done in the fleſh contrary to the will of God.</p>
            <p>Doctor, there muſt be a falling away, but not from God; but ſhall bring them neerer to God. It ſhall not be a falling from their Sabbath reſt, which is the endleſs Miniſtery of Chriſt; but it ſhall be a falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from your power, that the myſtery of iniquity may be diſſolved or diſcovered; for there muſt be a great falling away, and then you Stars, or Miniſters called, ſhall fall from your high perfection, and ſhall diſſolve before <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miniſters, you ſhall be much diſconſolate at this great falling away, when your ſheep ſhall ſeek a new Shepherd, and go to the right Shepherd Chriſt Jeſus, when the kingdoms and powers ſhall be all given into his hand: when no man ſhall ſay, I am a Prieſt or a Miniſter of God, then you high Doctors may ſay, How are the mighty fallen? How be our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of ſpiritual warfare periſhed, and we are counted as low as other men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> thy honour is going down, thy Temple is rent: for there will be a falling away from thee: two parts of the people ſhall fall away, and the other two ſhall be tryed in the fire of his jealouſie, for God will bring all things upon trial to prove who are ſincere, and who are not; and who will lay down life and all for him and who will not. This falling away from you will be a redeeming of the people to Chriſt, by bringing them out from your adulterous power of Miniſtery, which is not of Chriſt, but of men, and cannot ſtand, for yours is the Goſpel of men and not from above; your power is literal, and you as ſo many decoy-ducks, that deceive and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare many others, ſo do you captivate all thoſe that follow you, and neglect the principal of all, which is Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſai.</hi> 20. and 23. <hi>The Lord ſaith, He will make a conſumption in the midſt of the Land:</hi> which is now to be obſerved by this great falling away, as by a ſhaking or quaking of the people of God; which ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth they muſt fall from your Miniſtery, and be reſtored to Chriſt their great Conquerour.</p>
            <p>This Tribe of Chriſt, called the North-Tribe, ſhall grow and proſper until it come to be an invincible Tribe of the Lion of <hi>Judah.</hi> This Lion of the North ſhall cauſe all the beaſts of the field to quake, and a terrible
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118983:25"/> ſhaking ſhall be that have diſobeyed him. This great Conquerour Chriſt Jeſus of the new covenant, firſt appeareth to the Meſſenger of the covenant, and ſo to the North-country, by an aluſion to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>As I have ſcattered them, ſo will I gather them from the North country, and from all the countries where they have been ſcattered.</hi> Chriſt alone he ſhall gather the people, he is King of the North-country, and of all the countries: when his power doth ariſe it ſhall be as water in the bowels of the world; he ſhall gather the people, he ſhall ſit and rule upon his Throne, he is the Lion of the North-sk<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe power ſhall go forth.</p>
            <p>This Tribe of the North is the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> to whom every Tribe ſhall ſtoop and fall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.8. <hi>Judah thou art as a Lion, thy hand ſhall he upon the neck of thy enemies. Judah thou art as a Lion from the prey, and ſhalt ſtand up for the Scepter ſhall not depart from thee, nor a lawgiver from between thy feet, until Shiloh come, and unto thee ſhall the gathering of the people be.</hi> So that I finde this Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> ſhall gather in all the loſt Sheep of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to their fold, that Chriſt may ſeparate the Sheep from the Goats, which will be a great ſhaking and falling away from your Miniſtery. When God ſhall divide your Sichem, and deliver his people out of your hands to be taught of Chriſt, and taken from your mouth; Then they may joyfully ſay, Our Moon is ſet, and no darkneſs appeareth. The Lord is the light of our Temple.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh and laſt part of this Sermon is ſet forth to declare the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able dominion of the Son of righteouſneſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118983:25"/>
            <head>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> SOme Prieſts may ſay, <hi>We have faſted, we have prayed, we have ſighed and mourned for the people.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>All this may be, yet Chriſt hath done ſo before thee, for he hath laid his life down, and done the work thorowly, for all that can believe.</p>
            <p>Then Oh Prieſt, look to thine own ſoul, and take no charge of other mens ſouls; though <hi>Noah, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> ſhould pray for others, yet they can have an anſwer but for their own ſouls: for Chriſt is the end of all happineſs and ſalvation, he is the end of war: look upon <hi>Sion</hi> the City of ſolemniſie to ſee <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a quiet habitation, a peaceable dominion. When the people ſee, the Miniſtiners ſhall be aſhamed, when the Lord of Hoſtes ſhall raigne in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſit before his ancient glory to judge, when Chriſt ſhall ſit upon his throne by a Government called Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> by an Auditory of twenty four, or ſome twelves in other places to declare and effect condigne juſtice to all, according as God ſhall ordain and appoint without the help of man. Let no man ſay, He can teach: for no man can teach life and ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Then down with all teachers, that we may live under a peaceable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, our own Vine Chriſt Jeſus, for he will teach us of his wayes without all differing diſputations. Thoſe that call themſelves teachers, they live as drone-bees, by the ſweat of other mens brows. Therefore let them ſtop their mouths; for the people will not give ear to them, but will live under their own vine by a new Sabbath Covenantial: and you ſhall bewitch the people no longer: when fulneſs comes, God will teach, and the people ſhall declare what God hath done for their ſouls. Then all theſe Dromidaries of <hi>Midian,</hi> muſt break off your heavenly teaching, and come under the peaceable Dominion of Chriſt. You high Doctors, blame me not for ſpeaking; where life is, it will branch it ſelf forth. Who ſhall hinder my ſpeaking the truth? the ſilly Worm, to the cold Earth; the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander to the Fire; ſo all things to their proper uſe, to the honour of God.</p>
            <p>Oh that theſe rotten Prieſts would lay down their power, and make Chriſt all in all. Fat Prieſts that live as Drones, belly-godded perſons, proud and delicious, God is angry with you, becauſe no power will throw you down: God will give his people wiſdom to come out from you, and to live by a higher teaching, which is from the holy Ghoſt; for there will be a great falling away, that the iniquity of the Prieſts may be diſcovered. I have tried all your Miniſteryes, and can have no reſt in them, my ſpirit is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118983:26"/> ſo univerſally taken up with the appearings of Chriſt, that I unfailably ſee an abſolute doing away of your Forms, your Sabbaths, your Sacraments, your Baptiſm, your common-Churches, your ſeparate-Churches, your Anabaptiſt-Churches, your Papiſt Churches, all your ſet forms muſt return to the ancient Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which is the ſtable perfection of Chriſt; for now he apeareth all your forms muſt be done away. Chriſt at the firſt came under a ſtate of imperfection yeilding to the laws of men; but now he cometh in perfection, and will do away all your forms and ſhadows; for when that which is perfect is come, the unperfect muſt be done away.</p>
            <p>My deſire is to ſee the Prieſts thrown down, and let the Lord preach alone, for all the Miniſters under the cope of heaven, are not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine or make out the truth; neither can they ſpeak truth, till they give up their Miniſtery to Chriſt; for all teaching belongeth to him, and I know not any as can teach, but ſhall run themſelves into errors; for it is God that teacheth, and not fleſhly man; for by mans teaching the curſe hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued on the earth to this day: neither ſhall it be till Chriſt hath the full pre-eminency, and all powers yeilded up to him by an endleſs Covenant; ſaying, When that which is perfect is come, then that which is not ſhall be done away; when he cometh in power, your illegal forms and relecks ſhall be done away; for his formal power ſhall throw off your ſhadows, as all the creatures declare the glory of God, and preach forth his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; but not as a Prieſt to Miniſter in Chriſts place, but to ſhew what the Lord hath done for the creation, and to acknowledge Chriſt alone to teach life. He preacheth forth peaceable dominion to them that are nigh, and to them that are afar off: from him righteouſneſs doth ariſe, which is the end of all preaching; Chriſt is the ſtability of the Church, I do not ſay, of named Churches, but of one Church, without difference or dividual dividing; he is the husband of one ſpouſe, his perfection ſhall guide us unto all truth: and for want of ſetting up Chriſt in his oriency of power, men ſet themſelves up, and deſtroy his heritage; but the choſen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God muſt act againſt every thing that is oppoſite to Chriſt; for he is Prince of peace, and Prince of power, and for his cauſe ſacrifice thy life, otherwiſe thou art no Chriſtian: for we muſt look no more upon the Ark of the Covenant, it muſt not be once named amongſt us.</p>
            <p>The letter of the Scripture ſhall be failable: when the teſtimony truly, dwelleth in us by faith, then all our outward ſhadows ſhall be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; Chriſt hath redeemed us from all typical ſhadows, and from the curſe of the letter, being once made a curſe for us, that the bleſſing may come upon the people by faith, and not by literal forms and ſhadows, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Curſed is every one that hangeth upon a tree;</hi> Shewing the miſerable condition of all ſuch, that hold ſo much by the tree of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118983:26"/> Law, and deny the freedom of the Spirit they might have in the Son of God; for as many as rely upon works, are men-workers, lie ſtill under the curſe; for Chriſt is the free <hi>Abraham,</hi> he hath done all the work of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation, and we are free in him without works, and ſaved in him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mens works: if once in Chriſt, then free indeed from all mens tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional teaching; while we are juſtified in Chriſt, we acknowledge our ſelves ſinners, in that we ſee nothing in our ſelves, and Chriſt to be juſt in all. It is the believing <hi>Abraham</hi> that ſhall be juſtified, and not the working <hi>Abraham, For grace is of faith, and not by works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt:</hi> for if the inheritance be of the letter, it cannot be of faith. God gave it to <hi>Abraham</hi> as he believed, ſo the Lord promiſed to him and to his ſeed for ever according to the Covenant of faith, which is the Law and Teſtimony written in the conſcience, called two Witneſſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, which do Chriſtian a creature, and baptize him into the promiſed Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of <hi>Abraham</hi> and Chriſt, which is far above all your teaching forms and ſhadows.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak to the people, ſaying, Stand faſt in the liberty wherein Chriſt hath made you free, and be no more entangled with the yoke of bondage; but know your ſelves at liberty, as children of the day, and rejoyce with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> all that love her be glad and rejoyce, for the amplitude and ſtability of the Church; when all the Churches ſhall be maried to Chriſt in the new Covenant, that they may ſuck and be ſatisfied with the breſt of conſolation; for the Lord will extend peace to his Church as a river and to the people as a flowing ſtream, from a fountain of teaching from above.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>GOod men may ſometimes deny Chriſt, not knowing the end of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying.</p>
            <p>This Doctor <hi>Hill</hi> was an eminent man, (and without all queſtion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared forth many good things in his time, yet ſubject to erre as we be) by relation of ſome of the Souldiers, that quartered in the town of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> as they told me. I cannot tell, but as they related, a ſad ſtory of this Doctor <hi>Hill;</hi> by relation he was intended to perſecute with the tongue; whether right or wrong, his ſpirit knoweth it beſt, I cannot prove it; yet it was certified me. About ſome ſhort time before his end he was appointed to preach as he had formerly done, and went up into the Pulpit, and God gave him time to declare forth his text; and being inraged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome good people that were not of his judgement, fitted himſelf with words againſt thoſe that were not of his belief; and ſuddenly after he had
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118983:27"/> mentioned the words of his text, ſomething as it were twinged him, as if he had been ſtung. Lamented, ſaying, He was ſtricken; and ſo left off his preaching-diſcouſre; a ſad thing to think upon. I doubt many of your Prieſts are ſo taken with diſcontent, now God appeareth unto all fleſh: yet they think no fleſh like their fleſh, as when God giveth gifts to men below them they envy them, and preach againſt them, calling them opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onus-men, as if none be of the heavenly privy-counſel but they of the black guard, I mean Prieſts and Legators. Literal hiſtorian Prieſts, I muſt tell the truth, I am inwardly called and ſent to do it, I fear no fleſh, nor the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of any man; I muſt do my meſſage from God, though I die.</p>
            <p>SInce the time of <hi>Adams</hi> fall, the world hath been quartered out by the name of four beaſts, as a time, and times, and half a time lying under the rage of Antichriſtian power, contrary to the everlaſting Goſpel three times paſt, that the ſinful kingdom hath ruled over the kingdom of the Goſpel, by a beaſtlike power: and now is the fourth Monarchy, which we lie under, a diſpenſation, called the fourth beaſt or Monarchy, wherein the beaſt and falſe Prieſt ſhall be taken together, and ſhall uphold their power together by a comply, as if they cure the wound, and make the world to wonder; but they ſhall be taken by an extent from God, for in this fourth Monarchy, the time ſhall divide within the time, though they may ware out the Saints for a time, yet God will give the power of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy into their hands; though God may ſuffer for a time and times, yet <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, <hi>Judgement ſhall ſit to take away and conſume their power,</hi> Dan. 7.26. So that this fourth beaſt ſhall magnifie himſelf above other gods of the earth, and ſhall lift himſelf up in honors by blood, and ſhall extol his name, as high as the God of Gods; but time ſhall divide within his time, and judgement ſhall ſit, and he ſhall be taken with the Prieſts and the falſe Chriſts, and ſhall be cenſured for blaſphemy againſt the God of Gods, taking to themſelves ſuch high titles, as Lord and King. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2. <hi>The Lord ſhall be King of the earth, and ſhall rule many ſtrong Nations.</hi> Iſa. 2.17. <hi>The haughtineſs of man ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted.</hi> Iſa. 4.18. <hi>In that day the Lord will take away the bravery of their tinckling ornaments.</hi> Iſa. 9. <hi>Behold the children that the Lord hath given me are for ſignes &amp; wonders in Iſrael: when they ſhall ſay, Seek unto them that have familar ſpirits. The Lord ſaith, Shall not a people ſeek to their God? they have changed the Ordinances, trangreſſed and broke the everlaſting Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Prieſts ſhall fall by heaps, and their power will lie as low as Doctor <hi>Hill's</hi> bones; for the fifth Monarchial power ſhall put down their power and Prieſthood. I cannot fully declare my ſelf in this great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118983:27"/> myſtery of God preaching in fleſh. Therefore I confine my ſelf to end with much grief and ſorrow, deſiring to ſee truth magnified and all error trod down, that the Lord may be all our fort.</p>
            <p>ALl that love the appearing of Chriſts power, come out from the ſuttle deluſions deſtructive to Chriſt, and betroth your ſelves to him, that ye may be free from the ſeducings of men ſo miſerable and ſottiſh by their great conſpiracy againſt Chriſt, by their whitchcrafts and whoredoms. God will judge them that ſeek to wiſe men and counſellors, and not to the Lord, which is the principal; and ſo make men their teachers; but all Chriſtian propriety is called of the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. And I can call none Chriſtians till they fall off from beaſtion, and covenant to Chriſt in the new Covenant, and that is utterly to fall from their beaſtly power: he is a Chriſtian that lives up to Chriſt, without going to wiſemen for councel.</p>
            <p>The counſel of the Prieſts have alwaies ſeduced the people, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaking of the wiſdom of Chriſt, queſtioneth all things, ſaying, <hi>Where is wiſdom? It is not in me: it cannot be found in the creature: wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was before the creation. The ſea and the deeps give up, ſaying, It is not in me.</hi> So that we may pertinently finde, that Chriſt teacheth all wiſdom by the power of God, and he that wanteth wiſdom, let him ask of God that ſhall give him all things.</p>
            <p>Then throw off thy beaſtion wiſe men and counſellors, that keep thee from the Covenant of peace, and cauſe thee to deny thy marriage-union with Chriſt. Chriſt is the Husband of the Church, then why do you ſeek to fained lovers? Beaſtion durt-dawbers, that ſeek all wit, art and skill, to hold up their trade to ſecerate the people from the way of Chriſt, and ſee the blinde lead the blinde. Thou muſt be a great profeſſor, yet be thou what thou wilt, I cannot call thee a Chriſtian, until thou doſt quake and fall from all thy wiſe men and ſeducing councellors, I mean from all thy Pulpitian Prieſts, fully to come unto Chriſt; for there muſt be a falling away from the Prieſts, that the myſtery of iniquity may be diſcovered, and every beaſtly power diſſolved. Some of your Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Prieſts are ſo fat and yet full of frailty, very unconſtant and unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the truth, but Chriſt is our never fading hopes. Then look not ſo low upon men below Chriſt, having little or no percility in them, not living power in themſelves, then how ſhall they teach others to live: Let us go out to the fountain; for Chriſt is our immortality, he is the beginning and end of wiſdom, he teacheth in heaven and in earth. Then ſtop your mouths you beaſtians, that ye may may become Chriſtians, laying down all your bewitched forms, that contradict the truth of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118983:28"/>
            <p>MAn is not born to live to himſelf, neither can he croſs provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, <hi>The winde bloweth where it will;</hi> ſo God guideth the ſtern of all things, by a living providence, ſurmounting every pretended thing. My croſs is my outward loſs, if God will have it ſo. I am unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the world, God raiſed me up, and immediately caſt me down, which cauſed my ſoul not to look upon any outward intereſt, or ſelf-ſeeking hopes below Chriſt my Protector; for God is all in all to me, his intent hath been all along to drive me out of all earthly freedom, which proved hard and difficult to my thoughts, That I of neceſſity muſt throw up all worldly intereſt, to be leaſt in the world, if I did not, I could not be a faithful Diſciple, or a witneſs to Chriſt. Nature conſidered what a hard thing it would be to forſake wife and children, and calling too; yet I muſt do it, and that is my croſs, to follow my Saviour in his example, and not to be led by falſe Chriſts, or ſuch as you call Miniſters of God. And for that, I ſtand up, which doth anatomize my life. And as <hi>John</hi> loſt his life for Chriſt, ſo I lay down my life for him daily. I know my ſelf truly called to it: night and day I can have no reſt, the Lord is with me continually moving me in the work of the new Creation, and to go out a Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the power of <hi>Eliah,</hi> a Meſſenger to call in the <hi>Jews.</hi> If any one would take up my place, he cannot perform it; neither can I deny it, or put it off. Therefore let all godly ſouls mourn with me, for I ſhall be ſure of a ſolitary life, as an Anatomy ſhall I die, and the end of my pilgrimage is not known: and thus I give up all; yet I adviſe not every one to do ſo; but to walk up to that calling, that God hath called them to. I ſay, Judgement muſt ſit, and the Saints muſt judge the ends of the earth, for God is the beginning and the end of every work. I ſpeak as killed, &amp; yet alive; and though I die daily, yet I live, and my croſs doth anatomize my life, when I ſee the unſtableneſs and brevity of life, ſo changeable are all things under Chriſt, his brightneſs putteth out every light, he appeareth as the Sun. Let all be ſilenced.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>
               <hi>BAbylon</hi> ſhall down, with all her merchandizes: Gods people are commanded to depart out of her, the world doth lament her miſerable condition, ſaying, Alas, alas, and cannot help her; and being thus taken in the ſame ſnare with her, that they can do no
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118983:28"/> leſs but mourn with her, ſaying, How is our condition changed, and we brought low, that were ſo high exalted?</p>
            <p>The clamation is, ſaying, It is not your greatneſs, but your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that God eſteems, which cauſeth her to mourn, ſeeing her wants, ſaying, How art thou fallen from God in the world, and art become odious in his ſight? deſtitute, and art become the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Divels, and all unclean ſpirits, ſaying, We have recreated our ſelves in the world, and ſent gifts one to another in vain, for in a moment our condition is changed, and we left miſerable and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, cut off in our hopes: our iniquities have reached to heaven, and God is angry. Alas poor <hi>Babylon,</hi> how are we fallen? our Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, it is all diſcloſed. And thus <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt fall in all her practices of oppreſſion and covetouſneſs, and from every unlawful act, when all ſcoffers and jeerers ſhall be brought under this ſad calumny of hell in the world, which may then cauſe them to ſay, We be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our ſmoak, that aſcendeth up to heaven, and we juſtly ſee our burning, ſaying, Alas, alas, for in a moment it is come upon us, when all prophane perſons ſhall be laid out in the open view of Gods Church under the judgement of a community, bar'd out from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward temple, being left under a dark and a fearful diſpenſation, How may this terrifie the hearts of all unbelievers? when judgement is inflicted upon them, when they ſhall be ſhut out from the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of Saints, burning under the fire of Gods jealouſie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, hopeleſs and helpleſs. I pity your condition, all ye Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the world; for your earthly treaſures ſhall burn, and your ſorrows ſhall come unawares, and ye muſt fall at his appearing, and all the dark corners of the earth ſhall be made manifeſt and diſcovered by his kingdom. Alas poor <hi>Babylon,</hi> we cannot hide our decayes, upon Gods diſcovery, it is not our curioſity that can keep us; but if we be wicked, we muſt fall; for God will ſearch <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with torches, and much more you that diſobey him; he will prove all your works, and what is within us, and whether we be Hypocrites or Chriſtians, to know whether we be royal for him or no, otherwiſe we muſt burn and fall in her idolatry, and ſo be ſhut out of the land of the living, and lie in eternal deſpair. This <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall fall firſt at the preaching of the kingdom. Secondly, it ſhall penetrate and fall at the diſcovery of the outward court. Thirdly, it muſt fall at the building of the inward temple. Fourthly, it ſhall finally fall after the little book is opened, and the everlaſting Goſpel preached to ſhake both heaven and earth; meaning the godly and the wicked. There is a threefold ſhaking; firſt, of nations, to bring them all into one, which is to his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118983:29"/> kingdom; for all the kingdomes of the earth muſt become the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Lord, and yeild to his golden ſcepter. Secondly, there muſt be a great ſhaking of heaven or the heavenly people, Miniſters, &amp; others, to drive them of their own bottoms, ſo that every Chriſtian way ſhall be broken to pieces, and this burning from above ſhall caſhire all your opinions, that godlineſs may be one, and all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences ceaſe, that Chriſt may be one, and his name one, and his nation one to him. That unity may ſwallow up all differences, that they may ſerve him with one heart in love, and under one conſent. The third ſhaking, is, the earth or earthly mindes of men thus carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from God. And therefore they be called <hi>Babylon,</hi> which ſhall endure a terrible ſhaking, when the third part of the earth ſhall fall, which is Sodom, when God ſhall give up all her doings of cruelty to his holy ones. This ſhaking ſhall ſhake down all her power and pride, and all her domineering faſhions; which ſhall cauſe her to ſay, Alas, whither are we fallen, now our condition is changed, and we brought under our underlings? when our pompe ſhall be turned into emptineſs, and our wordly joy into mourning, it ſhall then ſhew apparently, that thou art fallen, and ſo ſoon as God calleth out his own people from out of thee, in that very moment and hour thou ſhalt burn and conſume till thou ſhalt be found no more. O <hi>Babylon,</hi> how ſoon will thy judgement come? What city was like this? and cry when they ſee her burning with ſpiritual fire; for in a moment our great riches are come to nothing: they that were made rich by her ſhall ſtand afar off, and ſee her burning, and dare not controverſe for her, nor hold up their hand to defend her; but ſhall cry, Alas, alas, ſuch is our condition, hopeleſs and helpleſs. This ſhall be her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, when <hi>Sion</hi> raigneth, and God ſhall ſever the one from the other, by a refining power. Here is a uſe of trial to all your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, to know and try your ſelves whether ye be of <hi>Canaan</hi> or not: if thou beeſt not, thou muſt burn with <hi>Babylon;</hi> for God will burn up all idolatry, he will conſume the wicked from off the earth. Therefore rejoyce over her ye holy ones, come to the feaſt of the Lord to eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire; for in her was found the blood of the martyrs. Come, may the Church ſay, Let us eat her up, for God hath given her into our hands; and Chriſt ſhall raign, and ſhall put all authority under his feet.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118983:29"/>
            <p>IT ſhall be a peaceable Dominion, when Chriſt ſhall raign over the Earth by a perſonal power of Saints, that ſhall fully hold forth the Scepter. He ſhall come to raign in power over the earth, till all rule and authority is put under his feet. Kings muſt throw down and ſtoop to his peaceable Dominion, he ſhall make ſtraight every crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed way, his endleſs Prieſthood ſhall teach, when every mouth ſhall be ſtopped, he giveth peace, which the world cannot give; he ſaith, Walk in my way, I will be your Sun, and your light, when every form and written declaration ſhall ceaſe and be no more. I would have all men live above the fleſh, by a heavenly procreation or inclination of doing good, and that is perfection indeed; for by doing well thou ſhalt have joy unſpeakable, which will be as a whole kingdom in thy ſoul.</p>
            <p>I would have Gods people preach forth reſtoration, and deſire to ſee a full manifeſtation of things made out, as the Lord alone to be all our teacher, he is our Protector and not man; his Prieſtly power ſhall be a peaceable Dominion, when Monarchy is put down, though Kings and Lord ſtands in his place, and Protectors ſtand in his place; yet who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth by a more brighter ſhining light, when all ſhall be forced to give up their dignities, &amp; ſtoop to his peaceable Dominion? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. <hi>I will ſend them to declare my glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles;</hi> ſhewing the great day of Jehovah, when men ſhall finally throw down their high titles, and then peaceable Dominions ſhall raign. <hi>What Prieſt will plead for my name?</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>againſt them that ſet themſelves ſo high, as Lord and King, and ſet themſelves up by earthly enjoyments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore God hath raiſed my Spirit to plead againſt all the Prieſts, and to lay open their folly that call themſelves Seers in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and yet keep all things as they were, ye have not yet preached the Goſpel; but denied the Son of God, and the power of his reſurrection; for ye have given his glory to men.</p>
            <p>Therefore as yet ye have not preached the Goſpel, nor laid your life down as yet for the truth. You have declared the Hiſtory of the Prophets, and of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> but we have had enough of it, without you would preach them out of their Graves. But which of you Prieſts will vindicate life for the eternal Goſpel? to ſet Chriſt upon his throne, to ſay he is King alone, and Lord alone, and ſo deny out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward honour, and acknowledge nothing honourable but the Lord, and that is true Goſpel, thou muſt tread down all for Chriſt, thou ſhalt tread upon Scorpions and Serpents, and they ſhall not hurt thee, it is the words of our Saviour; thou muſt tread upon Kings,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118983:30"/> Lords, and Princes, and Nobles, and Rulers, if thou beeſt true for Chriſt, he is the everlaſting Goſpel, thou ſhalt ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, it is the Lord that preacheth peace, &amp; keepeth all alive, fear not man, or any power of men formed againſt the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, it ſhall not proſper: when he appeareth, Kings muſt lay down, Princes muſt lay down, Protectors muſt lay down, Lords muſt lay down, Magiſtrates muſt lay down, Prieſts muſt lay down, thou muſt lay down, and I muſt lay down, the Stars and Conſtellations ſhall fail at his appearing, the negative voice ſhall not ſtand; for he will give power to his two witneſſes to plead for all truth, before a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat of the Saints, when this Government ſhall be taken away and changed at his bright appearing, when all formed Goſpels of men ſhall be changed to a new Sabbath, when men ſhall be forced to lay down for the Goſpel, when they ſhall aſcribe to him kingdom, power and glory, and that is the full end of preaching, to ſet God upon his throne; he is the everlaſting Goſpel of peace, and I know no other Goſpel, but that he ſhould rule above every man in dignity and honor. And that Lord, man ſhould not pollute his holy name.</p>
            <p>Ye high Doctors may Object, ſaying, <hi>What is the power of Chriſt you ſpeak ſo much of?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, It is the power of God, that ſhall ſilence the great mens ſpirits, when it ſhall apear, it ſhall take away their ſting, as from King, and Lord, and Biſhop, that have formerly perſecuted the Saints. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>All power is given me in heaven and earth;</hi> and God ſaith <hi>Vengeance is mine.</hi> I wonder how men dare do as they have formerly done, to put an end to ſome of Gods choſen people, by taking away life and free-creation, and by ſilencing ſome others in priſon, which is a type of hell, and dare not kill them, leſt heaven and earth ſhould cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, as that it hath done long ſince.</p>
            <p>Ye Miniſters go with your hands full of blood, by flattering men in their blood-thirſty-way, by ſowing pillows and cuſhions under their elbows, very loth to tell them the truth from God, ſaying, Why do you take away life and free-creation from the creatures of God? ſeeing life and death is in the hands of the Lord, then what hath man to do to take away life from any of the creatures of God? it is an intolerable thing: which of you Prieſts will ingage for Chriſt in this cauſe? ſaying, Oh great men, I doubt you will ſink in the lake of Gods irrecoverable vengeance; for vengeance is the Lords, and he will give it them to drink; <hi>for the Soul that ſinneth it ſhall die.</hi> Let men take heed how they act, and ſee that they act in righteouſneſs: better they had never been born, then to be bloody perſecutors, to offend
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118983:30"/> any of thoſe little ones of Chriſt, either by death or impriſonment.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>GOd teacheth us by his Son, he is the ſure word of propheſie, &amp; our everlaſting Goſpel which may reprove the literal teachers, that call the Scriptures the Goſpel, when indeed they are but the writings of men put together as a Hiſtory, but Chriſt is the eternal myſtery, Chriſt Jeſus alone is our eternal peace, free from failable mixture, it is God from the beginning; he is the word of life beyond the written word of man, ſo is the eternal decree in paradiſe, and as by a further manifeſtion of his Son to preach and declare forth all truth, far above the writings of men, which is not the word of God, but mans word ſpoken in part, nd propheſied in part, as <hi>Paul</hi> declareth.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Scripture cannot fully be called, the word of God, but mens traditions, and part of the minde of God, they propheſied in part, they writ in part, they believed in part of the myſtery of God; but Chriſt he comes in the volume of the book, he is our ſure word of propheſie, far higher then any Scripture, and for that cauſe Scripture cannot be fully called the word of God, except God hath writ it, Chriſt never pen'd down the myſtery, he is the final end of perfection. The promiſe was made in him 400 yeers before the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scripture; the promiſe was before the Law, and righteouſneſs came by faith, and not by local Scriptures, Chriſt opened the ſeals in order, <hi>He is the word from the beginning,</hi> John 1. The word was at the beginning, before the traditions of men were written, and ſhall ſtand till fulneſs come, which ſhall then be failable, perfection ſhall put an end to imperfection, when mans writing is done away, the Son of God is that wiſdom from the decree of God, to make out his full work, and ſhall ſtand when all mens Scriptures ſhall be failable, <hi>David</hi> cryes out in the 19 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Who knows the errors of his life?</hi> ſo that men and Prophets may be unſtable in their judgement.</p>
            <p>All Scriptures were written by the permiſſion of God, and men declared of things a far off, and could not fully ſpeak of things to come, but as they ſpake in part. <hi>Heaven and earth ſhall paſs away, but not one tittle of Gods word,</hi> which was his ancient decree from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; before men writ the Scriptures, his decrees were, and his councel ſhall ſtand; he ſpake the word, and it was done: if Scriptures could be the word of God, then common Chriſtians might write by inſpiration, and call it the word of God; which that they cannot do;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118983:31"/> for it is but mens declaration; &amp; yet the Prieſts ſay, They preach the word of God, though they deceive the poor people with the letter, men may be very plyant and prophetical as the Prophets were, and write many ſweet truths; yet the decree of God ſhall ſtand, when written words are failable, though they write after their judgements they ſhall be failable being yet in the fleſh; for Chriſt is our ſure word of propheſie, far above Scripture, to declare what the word is, firſt, it is God. Secondly, it is perfection. Thirdly, it is his councel and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree. Fourthly, it is ſpiritual light from above. Fifthly, it is a word of life that preacheth out from the mouth of God. Therefore the written letter is not the word of God, but put into them from a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ingenuity, or received of God by a ſpiritual power from above, being writ by failable man, that hath received in part of that full perfection. Chriſt is the full end of all myſtery, he preacheth upon the mount, hear him, with a laudable voice, he inwardly teacheth, his wiſdom is excellent, paſt finding out; mens writings and teachings are ſubject to change, but the word of God is the ſame from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not any thing of God ſhall fail, Mount Sion ſhall ever ſtand ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and firm, the Lord is unchangeable, though mens teachings fail, and Scriptures fail, and Prophets fail, and Prieſts fail, and all outward forms and ceremonies fail, though outward Sabbaths fail, yet the two witneſſes ſhall not fail, the two anointed ones ſhall ſtand before the God of the whole earth; if Chriſt and the Spirit dwell in us, they ſhall teach us how to live in all truth, though man in his ignorance lieth under the letter, and liveth altogether by line and verſe, the Law being a Schoolmaſter or Teacher to him, yet when he is redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Spirit, he walketh above the letter, knowing himſelf free, incorporated, and brought within the precincts of the glorious liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Son of God. Chriſt is the ſure word of propheſie, far higher then the Scriptures which the Doctors call the word of God, and is not, but part of the truth; but Chriſt ſhall endure when all mens wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings be as low as Doctor <hi>Hill's</hi> bones, and ſhall be failable before the great manifeſtation of the light that ſhall appear when all ſhall bend at the Scepter; his wiſdom teacheth all truth, men teach for envy, ſome for pride, and ſome for money, and ſome teach other mens works, and yet call it, the word of God, though they can declare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of the gift, but what they have received by learned phraſes, and much ſlight the word of the eternal Covenant, by adoring the writing and preaching of men, which are outward, literal, and not the word of God, but Scriptures of men, as Chronicles and Hiſtories, and ſhall be failable. I do not deny the good as is in the Scriptures,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118983:31"/> but I adhere to it, ſo far as it anſwereth to the righteouſneſs of God, and ſo far we ought to walk plyant to the Scriptures, as by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt, his rule ought not to be compounded with other mens works, but that his fame ſhould be ſeen alone; for by that means the Prieſts do preach mens praiſes more then the honor and authority of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now in all your learning, I deſire you would learn to know Chriſt the ſure word of propheſie, which is God alone, above the Scriptures; and ſo the Scriptures are but mens traditions laid together, chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled up, what good men had declared by hiſtory for a memorial or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for us that come after, and not to look for ſpiritual life by the Scriptures; for that is the free gift from above by his grace; but to look on them for an exhoraation. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>In the Scriptures ye think to have eternal life;</hi> yet he doth not ſay, <hi>In them there is eternal life;</hi> for he is life eternal, and he hath done all things well. Prophets, and Prieſts, and Men may write, yet of themſelves can eſtabliſh no truth, for Chriſt is the ſtable center of all, he is Almedium that preacheth in the Mount, he is our ſure word of propheſie, yet he writ no Scripture, nor declared himſelf by letter, yet many Scriptures have teſtified of him, he was and is exemplary to all.</p>
            <p>Therefore I would have all men live to the Lord, above that which is written of men; for what is written but ſhall be failable? or what light can keep its full oriency, before the Sun? every borrowed light ſhall be failable. I deſire men would not hang ſo much upon the letter, Chriſt Jeſus is unfailable; he is yeſterday, to day, and for ever. Let us ſet Chriſt above all literal Scriptures, which ſhall contingently fail: when he cometh in power he ſhall put an end to every work, Chriſt is the prime reality of all true integrity, he is the eternal word of life, all things live by the decree of God finiſhed in us, his promiſe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 400 yeers before any Scripture was writ, given to <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith, and not by Scripture, in that we ought to know ſomthing above the letter, which is the word of faith, a ſure propheſie, it is not the word preached, that can redeem us, except we have perſonal holineſs in us, by a right knowing of God by inſpiration, otherwiſe it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God; for men may hear Scripture preached, and yet not be happilized, and Prieſts may preach, and yet cannot ſave ſouls.</p>
            <p>Therefore ye high Prieſts lay down your authority, God teacheth from above, and will order his affairs above your art and policy, who ſhall learn him knowledge? ſhall <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> inſtruct his way? their places are inferiour to him, for Chriſt is our true word of propheſie, far above all art or pretended skill, God is the beſt Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118983:32"/> he will teach his people in all truth by an inward renewing the mind: if God teacheth, then let men lay down, and ſay, We cannot ſavingly teach; we preach the letter, but ſalvation is from above, he miniſtreth the gift of healing, and man cannot do it: Ordination is ceaſed with the Apoſtles, and God doth appear to us by his Son, and under the name of two witneſſes, which is the Law and Teſtimony within, that teacheth us better then all the Prieſts. Therefore I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire we may all ſee and live under the teachings of God, for he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us the myſtery of truth: let God be true, and every man a lyar: you <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Prieſts may prognoſticate the people, but Chriſt is the ſure word of propheſie, we will hear him with a laudable voice. The Prieſts ſay, Hear us, we will not be ſilenced: but for all this thou muſt be ſilenced Oh Prieſt, for Kings, and Lords, and Nobles, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhall be ſilenced, at his bright appearing, <hi>There ſhall be ſilence in heaven for the ſpace of half an hour,</hi> Rev. 8.1. Who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth by a dividing of time? I ſay, all you Miniſters have not yet preached the Goſpel, neither can any man preach the Goſpel at all, until he throweth down his own power of preaching, and make Chriſt your Prieſt and Teacher, and ſay you are no more a teacher of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a keeper of cattel from your fathers, and to work by the ſweat of your brows, for knowledge ſhall run to and fro, and meet by voices and witneſſes, that ſhall throw off and extinguiſh all your ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative voices, that ſtand deffinating ſo high in Pulpits: one witneſs of the Miniſter, or Prieſt of himſelf, is a negative untruth, and is centred upon meeſum, which is by a ſingular vote, and cannot ſtand; for it is Chriſt alone that ſhall ſtand to preach; for he is ordained and ſent as a Mediator of himſelf between God and man.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, I believe in ſhort time your people will be few in number; for then and at that time, the people ſhall betroth themſelves unto the Lord, and will refuſe your teachings; when they are inwardly taught of God, they ſhall remove from you Pulpits, and ye ſhall no more ſay to the people, <hi>Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me;</hi> that is, they ſhall all know Chriſt to be the Miniſter, and ſhall return to their firſt Love, from whence they were fallen, ſaying, Come, do thy firſt work; as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, Chriſtians, come enter into your reſt: once in him, and ever: he is our Sabbath and Goſpel of peace, he is unchangeable to the end, and that is a Sabbath indeed, it is not your keeping a day once a week, that can make a true reſt, it is the Sabbath within, having Chriſt dwelling in thee by a true faith, that is a Sabbath and a reſt that cannot be taken away, the receivings of Chriſt in thee quickeneth thee every moment from day to day, which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118983:32"/> ſheweth forth in thee a continual Sabbath, <hi>From yeer to yeer thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord, and keep the feaſt of Tabernacles,</hi> when a Chriſtian walketh in all outward righteouſneſs, that is a feaſt of one Tabernacle, and to walk by inward righteouſneſs, that is the other feaſt of Tabernacles, <hi>Ye ſhall once a yeer come up to keep the feaſt of tabernacles,</hi> Zach. 14. Theſe two Tabernacles, the one for an inward, the other for an outward, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led firſt and ſecond Tables, which ſhall be the worſhip that ſhall be ſet up from day to day, and yeer to yeer, until <hi>Shilo</hi> come.</p>
            <p>Prieſts, it is not for you to keep a day once a week, and be as evious as ever; it is not to keep a day, and be as covetous as ever; that is not a true Sabbath, Chriſt is the Sabbath, and he is our eternal reſt. And Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, thou muſt deny thy ſelf, if ever thou wouldſt enter into his reſt; for Chriſt ſweetneth all things to a Chriſtian, every doubt is comprehended and comprimized in him, he is the end of trouble, of war, and of every conflict, he is our Goſpel-peace to ſtill the rage of all obſtruction, and for want of making Chriſt our teacher, it cauſeth us to follow falſe Chriſts, I mean Prieſts and Jeſuites, that teach their own Goſpel, and ſet themſelves up by fat parſonages, feigned lovers to deceive the people, as if they had the minde of God at their will; Humble-bee-Prieſts, fat belly-goded-Parſons, to declare to the people once a week, as if God were tied to their ſet times: ſo as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, ſo do you, keep a day once a week, and yet crucifie the Lord, and ſo do ye, not knowing his eternal Sabbath.</p>
            <p>Ye ſilly people, I much condole your weakneſs, in that you ſo much i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolize the Prieſts, and neglect your onely true reſt. The Lord appeareth to us every day, aſwel as on that day, which thou calleſt the Lords day, and truely ye are as legal as ever the <hi>Jews</hi> were, though cunningly you call your Sabbath the Lords day, yet cannot take away your obſerved forms: the Lords day is every day.</p>
            <p>Therefore Prieſt throw down thy obſervation, Chriſt is the Sabbath of reſt, his day is every day, from yeer to yeer. Ye Doctors and Prieſtical Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, you are very cenſurous.</p>
            <p>I cannot but further relate a Pulpit-ſtory of this Doctor <hi>Hill,</hi> by ſome godly perſons of neer relation to him, having ſome diſcourſe with them, they did not comply with his element, but were a little contrary to his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not pleaſing to his allegation, which to affront them in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he thought to met with them in the Pulpit, took a text of Scripture to croſs them; but as I underſtood God met him in the way, and fruſtrated him in his firſt text; whereof he took another text, and in the ſame manner God met him again, and blaſted him upon his third ſubject, ſo that he judged himſelf ſtricken, and came down from the Pulpit, and related a ſad ſtory to ſome, that God juſtly puniſhed him, by reaſon of his inveterated ſpirit of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118983:33"/> bitterneſs, ſo that I finde God met him by way of etilliation, as we have an example in <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> the Lord puniſhed <hi>Jacob</hi> for taking his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Eſau</hi> by the heel. Therefore let no man think ſo low of his brother, but that God can ſpiritually raiſe men to higher knowledge, then <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> can do. And let not Miniſters and Doctors be ſo high, now God appeareth to the weak things of the world, to confound the haughtineſs of the proud; for we have a ſure word of propheſie, far higher then you can teach. Doctors and Miniſters, ye preach of a Prince that ruleth in the Air: I pray you, what is that? if you were as far from that, as you are from right diſciplying, you would have but little to do with it.</p>
            <p>Doctor, I muſt tell you what it is that ruleth in the Air, it is money, which is the King of all the creatures, that ruleth in the Air, it buyes, and ſells, and captivates all things under it; ſilver and gold bewitcheth the world, and you would ſpend your lives in the Pulpit for it, and it is called but the Prince that rules in the Air, and beguileth the Prieſts that preach for hire; Chriſts is a free-Miniſtery, and an endleſs Prieſthood; yours is failable.</p>
            <p>I can give relation of a Prieſt, that removed himſelf from about 40. <hi>l.</hi> a year, for a place of 300. or 400. <hi>l.</hi> a year. This Prieſt cunningly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched his people of the new place where he came, and in the midſt of his Sermon, related to them, That God had brought him thither in a cloud from the ſubſtance of 40. <hi>l.</hi> a year, to 300. <hi>l.</hi> a year. And was not this a cunning dawber to delude the people by a dark cloud?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Numbers, Leviticus</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> declareth, <hi>That the Prieſts ſhall have no inheritances:</hi> therefore I finde they that have bought Tythes and Impropriations, have bought and ſold that, which was none of their own. Lord Protector, I deſire you would give Tythes and impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the widows, the fatherleſs, the blinde, and the lame, and to the poor: as Chriſt would have it done, ſo let it be, that every Pariſh be eaſed of col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection; and praiſe God for the great good you have done for them. A poor meſſenger, a diſciple ſeparate for the kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I could have added much more to this work; but in ſhort I have declared ſome of the minde of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daynus,</hi> A meſſenger of the new Covenant, under the Ark-angel of the Covenant. As <hi>John</hi> was ſent a meſſenger to the <hi>Jews,</hi> to declare the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven at hand, ſo I <hi>Daynus</hi> am ſent to the whole Iſrael of God, to ſhew the kingdom of heaven is come in power to me, and I am the firſt upon the feet, reſtored of the dry-bones of Iſrael. <hi>Daynus,</hi> to ſhew the day and year of the Lord, and his year excepted.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118983:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
